<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The great charter for the interpretation of all prophecy of Scripture, and of the times defined by it: Pleaded, in justification of what hath been written thereupon, against the several imputations of curiosity, groundless presumption, phantastry, or enthusiasm.</title>
            <author>Beverley, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 190 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76491</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B2152</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R170522</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45097548</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45097548</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171163</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76491)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171163)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2563:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The great charter for the interpretation of all prophecy of Scripture, and of the times defined by it: Pleaded, in justification of what hath been written thereupon, against the several imputations of curiosity, groundless presumption, phantastry, or enthusiasm.</title>
                  <author>Beverley, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>For the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Author and imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lambeth Palace Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible --  Prophecies.</term>
               <term>Apocalyptic literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:171163:1"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Great Charter</hi> FOR THE INTERPRETATION OF ALL Prophecy of Scripture, AND OF The TIMES Defined by it: PLEADED, In Juſtification of what hath been Written there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, againſt the ſeveral Imputations of Curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſity, Groundleſs Preſumption, Phantaſtry, or Enthuſiaſm.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>2 <hi>PET.</hi> I. 20.</bibl>
               <q>Knowing this firſt, That no Prophecy of Scripture is of any private Interpretation.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IT is very Notorious, there is nothing Learned, and good Men are more Scandalized at, or give ſlighter Regard to, throughout all that is offered to them from the <hi>Word of God,</hi> than the Interpretation of <hi>Scripture Prophecy;</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, if Any come to the Interpretation of thoſe <hi>Prophecies</hi> that Define Time.</p>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:171163:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:171163:3"/>
            <p>Now this ariſes from a ſtrong Pre-judgment or Pre-poſſeſſion of Mind, That ſuch <hi>Prophecies,</hi> and moſt particularly concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Time,</hi> are not poſſible, or hardly Lawful to be <hi>Interpreted,</hi> and that it is preſumption to offer at it; and that all that is drawn from ſuch <hi>Interpretation,</hi> is no other than Groundleſs Phantaſtry.</p>
            <p>I have therefore Reſolved, ſince the Lord, as I Truſt, hath Himſelf engaged my <hi>Labours</hi> in this his <hi>Vineyard,</hi> to make it my Humble endeavour to Explorate, and to Find out by this Scripture, How far ſuch Attempts of <hi>Interpretation</hi> are Juſtified, and the Succeſs aſſur'd by the <hi>Word of God:</hi> Now, this Text, and the whole Context ſeem, even at the firſt ſight, to give Higheſt Countenance and Favour hereunto; for it expreſly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms, <hi>No Prophecy</hi> of <hi>Scripture,</hi> not of <hi>Daniel,</hi> or of the <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> or any other <hi>Scripture Prophecy,</hi> nor of the <hi>Numbers,</hi> rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to Time in thoſe <hi>Prophecies,</hi> and wherein the preciſeneſs of Times is Depoſited and Lay'd up, is of <hi>Private Interpretation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I begin therefore with the Conſideration of the Direct Terms, or Words of this ſo Full Propoſition of the Apoſtle:</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Subject-Matter, concerning which the Apoſtle thus affirms, is not <hi>Scripture</hi> in general, but moſt particularly <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy of Scripture;</hi> If his Propoſition had been upon Scripture in general, it had neceſſarily included <hi>Prophecy of Scripture</hi> in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular; Becauſe <hi>Prophecy</hi> is ſo excellent a part of <hi>Scripture;</hi> but it is Greater, and more Emphatical, that He particulariſes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Prophecy</hi> it ſelf.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Care the Apoſtle hath Taken to ſhew it is the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſality of <hi>Scripture-Prophecy,</hi> He thus aſſerts concerning <hi>All Prophecy</hi> of <hi>Scripture,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; which imports, <hi>All Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy;</hi> and <hi>Every Prophecy. All Prophecy</hi> in general, and <hi>Every Prophecy</hi> in particular is the ſubject ſpoken of; and therefore a Word is choſen out by the Spirit of God, that may fully An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer thereunto in both regards.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That to which the Apoſtle directs his Speech, is not with Relation to the Excellency, or Certainty, or Divine Inſpiration of <hi>Scripture Prophecy</hi> it ſelf; although that He does alſo in the former Verſe, calling it the <hi>Sure Word of Prophecy;</hi> and by way of proof in the next Verſe, of what he affirms in this: But that which He is preciſe upon in this Verſe Relates to <hi>Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Scripture Prophecy.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:171163:3"/>
            <p n="4"> 4. That which He fixes upon as to his Point, to conſider concerning <hi>Interpretation,</hi> is concerning the <hi>Privacy</hi> of it; Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it is a Publick, Free, Open, Acceſſible, Self-communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Thing; or whether Private, Reſerv'd, Uncommunicated, or under Any ones Propriety and Encloſure, ſo that no other may Preſume to Enter into the <hi>Interpretation</hi> of it, but under ſome Character for ſuch a Propriety?</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Form of the Apoſtle's Propoſition is a flat and down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Negative; <hi>Scripture-Prophecy, All Scripture-Prophecy, Every Scripture Prophecy</hi> is ſo Conſtituted, Framed, Deſcended, as not to be of <hi>Private Interpretation;</hi> and that the Negation may be the ſtronger, It is Kept, and Reſerved to be placed with the Full ſtrength of its Accent upon the Words, <hi>Is not private:</hi> The Apoſtle would not leſſen it by ſetting <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in place of <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, both for the Force of the Word of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſality</hi> before Noted, as alſo, That the Negative might urge the more, being applied to <hi>Private;</hi> And ſo it amounts to a ſtrong Affirmation; on the other ſide, it is of an <hi>Interpretation,</hi> Open, Publick, Free; a Common Good and Right.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The Apoſtle lays it as a Foundation, as a firſt Principle, <hi>Knowing</hi> (ſaith He) <hi>this firſt, That All Prophecy of Scripture is not of a Private Interpretation.</hi> And it comes in as a ſtrong Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument or Motive for what he had ſpoken, by way of Vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Incitation to the <hi>Taking Heed to Prophecy;</hi> for ſaying That Every one <hi>did well, who Took Heed to the More ſure Word of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy.</hi> He goes on by way of Encouragement, and Aſſurance of Good Succeſs, <hi>Knowing, That It is of an Open, Ftee Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi> or being well principled in that firſt, as is after to be urged.</p>
            <p>Now who that Conſiders theſe Words of the Apoſtle thus pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, and lay'd out before Him, and what <hi>The Spirit</hi> by his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Miniſter hath ſpoken thus, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſo <hi>expreſly</hi> can have a preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice againſt All utmoſt Endeavour to <hi>Interpret Any, Every Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Scripture,</hi> and contradict the Holy Ghoſt; ſaying, It is a Dark, Retired, Reſerved Thing; not to be preſum'd upon, or to be medled with.</p>
            <p>But before I proceed upon the main Points ariſing from this Propoſition of the Apoſtle, in Juſtification of Interpretation of <hi>Scripture-Prophecy;</hi> I am very ſenſible, the very Foundation is endeavoured to be ſhaken by ſuppoſiting, or ſhifting in another word for <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <hi>Interpretation,</hi> viz. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a word differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but an <hi>Iota,</hi> an <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; and ſo may ſeem fair for admiſſion;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:171163:4"/> and a word that would be had, to ſignify <hi>Inſpiration;</hi> or if that be not found ſo convenient to Change the word; yet it is Deſigned to Bring the Matter to the ſame Point by giving a ſenſe to it foreign to this Point, <hi>viz</hi> by affixing to <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a ſenſe the ſame with <hi>Inſpiration; viz.</hi> Diſmiſſion or ſending out the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets;</hi> that ſo either way the Apoſtles Propoſition might ſpeak thus: <hi>Knowing this firſt, That no Prophecy of Scripture is of a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate</hi> Illaps, or <hi>Inſpiration;</hi> and ſo <hi>Interpretation</hi> ſhould have no place, nor any thing to do here.</p>
            <p>I will therefore Argue, firſt againſt any other word, than that of <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and then againſt any other ſenſe of the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but that of <hi>Interpretation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Arguments that the word <hi>Epiluſis,</hi> and not <hi>Epeluſis,</hi> was uſed by the <hi>Divine Spirit,</hi> are theſe two.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There is an Univerſal Conſent, and Agreement of All Coppies in the word <hi>Epiluſis,</hi> wherein that Providence watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full over All Scripture, hath particularly ſhewn it ſelf in care over this; ſo that there is no occaſion for any one to Change it, except He Himſelf were <hi>Given to Change,</hi> or would make an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt againſt it, becauſe He would not own the <hi>Prophecy</hi> (at leaſt) <hi>of Scripture,</hi> to be of a Free, Open, Publick <hi>Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> nor to be Approached unto.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is obſerved by the Learned, The word <hi>Epeluſis</hi> is not the proper word to ſignify <hi>Illaps,</hi> or <hi>Inſpiration,</hi> or any thing like it; But the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as it comes ſomething near the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and yet can never be it, or the ſame; ſo it ſeems ſomewhat a-kin in ſenſe to Super, or Preternatural Emo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but at ſo great a diſtance, It can never be Divine Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural, nor like it, but moſt Contrary to it, and Abhorred of it: For it is a word of very ill Intention, and ſignifies the Force of Enchantment on the Enchanted Perſon; a ſenſe that can by no means be ſuffered to Enter into the <hi>Tabernacle</hi> of the <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> the Spirits of his <hi>Prophets;</hi> nor Agree to the Sacred ſcope and purpoſe of the Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>But I will yet further Argue againſt any other word, but <hi>Epiluſis</hi> in Arguing againſt any other ſenſe, but that ſole and ſingle ſenſe of <hi>Interpretation;</hi> ſo that by <hi>Epiluſis</hi> ſhall not, cannot be underſtood, as ſome would have it, any kind of <hi>Diſmiſſion,</hi> or <hi>ſending</hi> out the <hi>Prophets</hi> to <hi>Prophecy.</hi> For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The very ſame word, differing only as a Noun and a Verb, that is uſed here by the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> is uſed in the very
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:171163:4"/> ſame Senſe, and in the very ſame matter, and purpoſe, <hi>Mark</hi> 3. 34. Only what is denied here by this Apoſtle is affirmed in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Caſe there, <hi>viz.</hi> Our Lord <hi>Expounded</hi> his <hi>Parables</hi> but <hi>Apart</hi> or <hi>Privately</hi> to his <hi>Diſciples:</hi> There <hi>Epelue,</hi> He Expounded <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>Apart;</hi> Here the <hi>Expoſition</hi> or <hi>Interpretation</hi> of <hi>Prophecy</hi> is <hi>denied</hi> to be <hi>Apart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Scripture in <hi>Mark</hi> therefore is, as if the Spirit of God had on purpoſe provided an Aſſurance, in what manner theſe ſame Words are to be underſtood in <hi>Peter, viz.</hi> by the Certain, Undoubted Senſe of them in <hi>Mark:</hi> And it is the more to be Noted, if we give heed to the <hi>Eccleſiaſtic Memoir,</hi> that, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſuper-intended the <hi>Evangeliſt Mark</hi> in his Writing that <hi>Goſpel:</hi> Obſerve therefore, The ſame Divine Spirit by the very ſame Servant of his, the Penman of this <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> and the Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſor of that <hi>Goſpel,</hi> uſes both Words; the word ſo much the ſame with <hi>Epiluſis,</hi> ſo undoubtedly in the ſenſe of <hi>Expounded;</hi> and of <hi>Privately,</hi> or <hi>Apart</hi> in the Word <hi>Idios;</hi> and that they are us'd both Affirmatively, and Negatively in the ſame ſenſe: For what the <hi>Evangeliſt</hi> ſpoke Affirmatively, <hi>viz.</hi> Chriſt did <hi>Expound</hi> or <hi>Interpret</hi> but <hi>Apart,</hi> that the Apoſtle in this Text lays down in the Negative, or denies concerning the ſame <hi>Expoſition</hi> or <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation, viz.</hi> That it is not <hi>Apart</hi> or <hi>Private.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is ſo full in this kind of Argument, that it ſeems unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to add; It is the word uſed by the <hi>Septuagint,</hi> for the <hi>Interpretation</hi> of the <hi>Dreams</hi> of <hi>Pharaohs Officers</hi> by <hi>Joſeph,</hi> Gen. 41. 82.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But that which is indeed above All, is, The Reaſon, and Scope of the Apoſtles Diſcourſe, require the word, <hi>Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and no other; For the Apoſtle was not Preſſing, that the word of <hi>Prophecy</hi> is a <hi>ſure Word;</hi> That He knew, was Agreed, and moſt acknowledged between Him, and the <hi>Hebrew Strangers ſcattered Abroad,</hi> to whom He wrote, and ſo the Apoſtle takes that for a moſt confeſſed Thing, and that they <hi>gave heed to</hi> it, as ſuch; but that which required immediately to be further ſpoken to, was, That the <hi>ſure Word</hi> of <hi>Prophecy ſhines,</hi> as a <hi>Light</hi> in the <hi>dark place,</hi> in which the Churches of Chriſt are, till the <hi>Day</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of Chriſt <hi>dawn,</hi> and He the <hi>Phoſphor,</hi> and <hi>Day-Star</hi> of it <hi>ſhine into the Hearts</hi> All His; For that is every where the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of that <hi>Kingdom,</hi> it firſt <hi>dawns,</hi> and then it <hi>ſhines,</hi> and it ſhines into All Hearts, poſſeſſes All Minds; The <hi>Day</hi> of Goſpel-Light, and the <hi>Day-ſtar</hi> of that had already ſhone; for they were <hi>Eſtabliſhed in the preſent Truth;</hi> but that the Apoſtle intended,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:171163:5"/> was to come; For He ſays, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntil it ſhine,</hi> which could not be properly ſaid of what is paſt: Beſides, That could not be come, that was yet in <hi>Prophecy,</hi> and needed <hi>Prophecy</hi> to <hi>ſhine</hi> in the place of it; which <hi>Place</hi> had been altogether <hi>Dark,</hi> if it had not been for the <hi>Light</hi> of <hi>Prophecy:</hi> And the <hi>Darkneſs</hi> of it was, becauſe that <hi>Day</hi> did not yet <hi>Dawn,</hi> nor the <hi>Day-Star Ariſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to this <hi>Light</hi> of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>You do well to Take Heed,</hi> you <hi>do well,</hi> as it is your Duty ſo to do; and as it is honourably well; So it is ſaid; <hi>Bleſſed is He that Readeth, and They that Hear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to this, This Objection might well be made; It is a great difficulty to underſtand <hi>Prophecy;</hi> who, or how few are agreed about the <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>Interpretation</hi> of it? and eſpecially in what relates to the Time of it, and thoſe Numbers relating to Time ſo particularly in <hi>Daniel.</hi> This therefore the Apoſtle would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, and ſurprize before hand, and He does it by laying this, as a firſt <hi>Principle, That All, and every Prophecy of Scripture is not of Private Interpretation;</hi> If it were ſo, it were indeed vain to <hi>Take Heed</hi> to it, as to a <hi>Light ſhining in a dark place,</hi> for then it would be as dark, as the <hi>dark place</hi> it ſelf; A <hi>Prophecy</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> that cannot be <hi>Interpreted,</hi> can no way enlighten the <hi>Dark</hi> State of the Non-appearance of the <hi>Kingdom:</hi> But the Apoſtle aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, the <hi>Sure word of Prophecy</hi> is not <hi>Private,</hi> Secret, Apart, but of an Open, Ftee <hi>Interpretation,</hi> is full to the Purpoſe of <hi>Taking Heed,</hi> or <hi>Giving Attendance</hi> to it, as to ſuch a <hi>Light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And then the Apoſtles following words evince the ſame Thing; <hi>Prophecy came not of old Time by the will of Man;</hi> But <hi>Holy Men of God</hi> ſpake, as they were <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Carried, Moved, Inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> by the Holy Spirit, as is further to be Explain'd: Now this comes as a Reaſon of what had been ſaid before, as is manifeſt by the Particle <hi>For;</hi> And it is, indeed, a great Reaſon, why no <hi>Prophecy</hi> of <hi>Sceipture</hi> ſhould be of a <hi>private Interpretation;</hi> becauſe it was given, as ſhall be ſhewn, from the <hi>Publick Spirit,</hi> and not from a <hi>Private Spirit,</hi> as every Created Human Spirit is.</p>
            <p>But if we underſtand the word us'd for <hi>Interpretation,</hi> to ſignify either <hi>Illapſe,</hi> or <hi>Inſpiration,</hi> theſe following words would be only words of Amplification, and not of Proof; and to be Interpret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as the oppoſite to <hi>Private,</hi> by the Adverſative <hi>But;</hi> and not Ratiocinative as the Cauſal Conjunction <hi>For,</hi> aſſures them to be. And the ſenſe muſt run thus; No <hi>Prophecy</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> is of <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Interpretation;</hi> But <hi>Holy Men</hi> of <hi>God ſpake, moved by the Holy Spirit;</hi> and if any one ſhould put in <hi>For,</hi> after <hi>Inſpiration;</hi> or <hi>Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſe</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:171163:5"/> ſuppos'd in place of <hi>Interpretation;</hi> It is as if the Apoſtle had ſaid, It is not of <hi>private Inſpiration,</hi> and therefore of <hi>Divine;</hi> For there can be no oppoſite to <hi>Private,</hi> but <hi>Divine</hi> in the Apoſtles ſenſe, and therefore it is not of <hi>private Inſpiration;</hi> Becauſe, or, For, <hi>Holy men</hi> were not <hi>Privately,</hi> but <hi>Divinely Inſpired;</hi> which is Amplification, and not Probation: But if we take, as on all Accounts we ought, the word to be <hi>Interpretation,</hi> the <hi>For,</hi> comes in moſt juſtly, as introducing a Great Reaſon, Why <hi>Prophecy</hi> cannot be of <hi>private Interpretation,</hi> becauſe it is of <hi>publick Inſpiration,</hi> as ſhall be ſhewn; How ſtrong a Reaſon is this!</p>
            <p>Now ſeeing Probation, or Proof, makes a Diſcourſe ſtronger than Amplification only; If there be any doubt concerning a word, Whether This or That? That ought to be preferred which makes the Sacred Text more Sinewy and ſtrong, and ſo does the word <hi>Interpretation</hi> here: And ſeeing there is ſo much for that word, and nothing againſt it, it ought to be acquieſced in by All, as offering ſo great a Truth; That we ought as in Hearing, ſo in Preaching, to give the ſenſe of <hi>Prophecy;</hi> as it is ſaid of <hi>Ezra</hi> and the other <hi>Levites,</hi> and the People under them, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 8. 7. <hi>They gave the ſenſe of the Law,</hi> and <hi>Cauſed the People</hi> to <hi>underſtand,</hi> the <hi>Reading,</hi> or <hi>Preaching;</hi> that is, the inward ſenſe of it, and not only the Syllabical Reading loſt in <hi>Babylon;</hi> as ſome may ſuppoſe; For that is beneath the Holy Spirits notice: And thus ought <hi>Prophetical Scripture</hi> to be Adminiſtred; Becauſe it is not of <hi>private Interpretation.</hi> It, and the Time of it, ought to be opened, and explained, All and every part in all its Divine ſenſes.</p>
            <p>But that, further yet, This point of <hi>Interpretation</hi> may be ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled, and ſecured, and not only ſo, but highly illuſtrated; I will endeavour to clear, that the Grand Importance of the Context, nay, of this whole Epiſtle, is Adjuſted and Prepared to Aſſure, That <hi>Prophecy of Scripture</hi> is not of a <hi>Private Interpretation</hi> in that great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Point of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of our <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and the Time of it; That <hi>Myſtery of God to</hi> be <hi>Fulfilled, Evangelized</hi> by <hi>All his Prophets,</hi> that <hi>Reſtitution of All Things</hi> in that <hi>Kingdom ſpoken of by All the Prophets, ſince the World began:</hi> Now of this <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> and the Time of it, The Apoſtles Affirmation, The <hi>Prophecies</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> are not of any <hi>private Interpretation,</hi> when and in what they ſpeak of it, hath the chief, and moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent place; And therefore the Diſcourſe upon ſo great a Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſo levelled, and prepared (as I may ſay) to all intents and purpoſes, for the Juſtification of ſearch into <hi>Prophecy,</hi> concerning
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:171163:6"/> the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> and what, ot what <hi>manner of Time,</hi> the Spirit of God hath ſignified, is, indeed, a <hi>Magna Charta</hi> for <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>Now then, the occaſion of all the Context, is the mention of the <hi>Abundant Entrance</hi> into the <hi>Kingdom of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and That, an <hi>Everlaſting Kingdom:</hi> Now of this <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> there is a Twofold ſtate; That which is now at preſent and by way of preparation, or the <hi>Miniſtration of an Entrance;</hi> and concerning that, The Apoſtle ſays, They <hi>were eſtabliſhed</hi> in the <hi>preſent Truth.</hi> 2. There is a Future State, and Glory of that <hi>Kingdom,</hi> which is that <hi>Everlaſting Kingdom,</hi> and to which this <hi>preſent Kingdom of Grace Miniſters</hi> an <hi>Entrance;</hi> and of this, ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>I will not be negligent to put you in remembrance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon this <hi>Baſis</hi> or Foundation laid then, I will firſt give great Arguments, That through the whole Epiſtle, and particularly in this Context, the Apoſtle hath very great Relation to this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and moſt particularly to the Time of it. 2. That the Context having ſo great Relation to this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly to the Time of it alſo, there is great Reaſon the Apoſtle ſhould ſpeak concerning the <hi>Interpretation</hi> of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> as the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Point, and that <hi>Inſpiration</hi> ſhould Attend upon it; In the firſt Part I will give Arguments, Firſt, That the <hi>Kingdom</hi> is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended; And then in the ſecond place, for the <hi>Time,</hi> as intended alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argument</hi> 1. That which I have already ſaid is moſt manifeſt; That the mention of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Diſcourſe before made haſte, and to which the whole Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle after iſſues, hath immediate Relation to this Context: For the Connexion and Coherence is ſo cloſe and ſtrict, that there is no dividing the one from the other; as will appear in the following Particulars. For,</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Apoſtle gives notice what <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> He had regard to, when He Styles it in <hi>Remembrance</hi> of that <hi>Kingdom</hi> Promiſed in <hi>Daniel,</hi> the <hi>Everlaſting Kingdom,</hi> as it is there Styl'd, <hi>C.</hi> 7. an <hi>Everlaſting Dominion,</hi> and a <hi>Kingdom, that ſhall not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. In that ſo Emphatically, He gives the Title of <hi>Saviour</hi> to <hi>Chriſt;</hi> as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> joyns the appearance of the <hi>Great God,</hi> and our <hi>Saviour Jeſus Chriſt</hi> together: For therein above All Chriſt is ſeen, and will be known to be the <hi>Saviour,</hi> Reſtoring All that was Ruined by the ſin of the <hi>Firſt Adam.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:171163:6"/>
            <p n="4"> 4. The great care the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> expreſſes, They ſhould have that Kingdom in remembrance, although they were eſtabliſh'd in the <hi>preſent Truth,</hi> that Miniſters but an <hi>entrance</hi> into that <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam;</hi> as was intimated before.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> as the <hi>New-Teſtament</hi> generally does, calling the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> his <hi>coming,</hi> remembers the Admonition <hi>Chriſt</hi> gave him of hss dying, or <hi>putting off that Tabernacle</hi> before he ſhould ſo come; whereas the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> had an expectation of that <hi>Kingdom</hi> immediately, as they ſaid; <hi>Wilt thou at this time restore the Kingdom to Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> giving ſo full a Repreſentation of the <hi>Transfigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> which was it ſelf an admirable <hi>Landſkip,</hi> and a Model of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, gives it on purpoſe to foreſhew it; the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> therefore gives it in Terms moſt expreſſive of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> v. 16. to v. 19.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is called the <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Coming of Chriſt,</hi> and the word <hi>Maſeſty</hi> imports Royal Greatneſs, <hi>v.</hi> 16.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſollemn Inauguration of <hi>Chriſt</hi> by the <hi>Voice from</hi> the <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent glory; This is the beloved Son, in whom I am well pleaſed;</hi> like unto that other ſo great Declaration of him. <hi>Thou art my ſon, this day have I begotten thee, when he ſet his Kingdom on his holy hill of Sion,</hi> v. 18.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As the <hi>New-Jeruſalem,</hi> the Palace of the Kingdom of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is an exceeding high and holy Mountain, ſo all this glory was on the holy Mountain.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In that the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> is ſo apprehenſive, it might be ſuſpected to be a <hi>cunningly deviſed Table,</hi> which Caution of the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a great Key of this whole Diſcourſe; and will lead us into the reaſon of this Context, as ſhall appear after.</p>
            <p n="5">5. In that the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> paſſes ſo immediately from the <hi>Transfigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> to the <hi>ſure Word of Prophecy,</hi> and to <hi>prophecy ſhining as a light in a dark place;</hi> by which two Characters put together, it manifeſtly appears the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> intended is neither the <hi>Kingdom of Grace,</hi> the Spiritual Kingdom, the Goſpel of Grace, as we generally ſpeak; nor the <hi>Kingdom of Eternity;</hi> not the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Grace:</hi> becauſe not only Prophecy looks to things to come, if ſtill in <hi>Prophecy,</hi> and to be fulfilled; but alſo if it ſhould be ſuppos'd: That <hi>Prophecy ſhin'd</hi> in that <hi>Kingdom of Grace,</hi> and of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> by the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> ſo Illuſtrious Miniſtry; that could be by no means called a <hi>dark,</hi> or ſqualid or <hi>foul place:</hi> For it was the Gloriouſeſt State of the <hi>Kingdom;</hi> and of <hi>Prophecy</hi> fulfill'd in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:171163:7"/> it, that had been ever before, or hath been ſince, or that ſhall be, till that very <hi>Everlaſting Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> come into its ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion; then it could not be the <hi>Kingdom of Eternity,</hi> For the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> of <hi>Eternity</hi> is not the manifeſtation of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> but one of the plaineſt and moſt Fundamental Doctrines of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and of <hi>Chriſtianity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I come therefore to the ſecond thing; that this <hi>Epiſtle</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtle Peter</hi> is adjuſted to, and that is, to the ſhewing the time of the <hi>Kingdom;</hi> for which I give theſe Arguments.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> calls it the <hi>Everlaſting Kingdom;</hi> by which; as was before intimated, he refers to <hi>Daniel's Prophecy</hi> of that <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Kingdom</hi> and <hi>Dominion, Dan.</hi> 7. 27. which is poſtpon'd to four <hi>Kingdoms</hi> and <hi>Monarchies,</hi> the laſt of which was then in courſe, when the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> wrote this; and to the laſt ſtate of which, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Feet of Iron and Clay,</hi> and the <hi>ten Horns,</hi> and a little one chief of the <hi>Ten,</hi> there was an allowance of <hi>Time, Times</hi> and <hi>Half a Time,</hi> before the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> could come into its Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Apostle</hi> by ſaying, <hi>The ſure word of prophecy ſhines as a light in a dark place,</hi> intimates, it foretels the time of that glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Kingdom;</hi> how could it ſhine ſo effectually, as to <hi>enlighten the dark place,</hi> if it gave no Knowledge, when <hi>Prophecy</hi> ſhould be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill'd. For that <hi>Prophecy</hi> does not paſs immediately into effect, made the ſpace between the appearance of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in <hi>Fleſh</hi> and in <hi>Glory dark:</hi> and therefore the <hi>light</hi> of <hi>Prophecy</hi> gives us a direction upon the Time, when the eflect of <hi>Prophecy</hi> ſhall be, the hope and aſſurance of which Enlightens.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> according to other <hi>Scriptures,</hi> diſtinguiſhes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>day dawning,</hi> and the <hi>Day-Star ariſing;</hi> one ſignifying the ſucceſſion of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt;</hi> the other the glory of that <hi>Kingdom.</hi> So the <hi>Myſtery</hi> of God is to be fulfilled in the days of the <hi>Seventh Angel,</hi> and then Chriſt appears in his Glory. So the <hi>Apostle</hi> diſtinguiſhes between <hi>Chriſt blaſting</hi> the <hi>man of ſin</hi> with the <hi>Breath of his Mouth;</hi> which is by the mighty power of the <hi>Everlaſting Goſpel,</hi> and then utterly conſuming and anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilating Him, with the <hi>Brightneſs of his Coming,</hi> or <hi>Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> deſcribes the <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> that ſhould ſo long delay the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> in <hi>myſtical</hi> Terms, under the <hi>ſhade</hi> of <hi>Nicolai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aniſm,</hi> and <hi>Gnoſtiſciſm,</hi> ſo fit to type out the <hi>Idolatry,</hi> impurity of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:171163:7"/> 
               <hi>Manners,</hi> and all the <hi>Abominableneſſes</hi> of the <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> State; of which <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> the <hi>little Horn</hi> in <hi>Daniel,</hi> whoſe repreſentation <hi>Daniel</hi> gave, as thinking to <hi>change Times</hi> and <hi>Laws,</hi> until the time <hi>of the Kingdom of Chriſt;</hi> Now of this very <hi>changing Times</hi> and <hi>Laws,</hi> is the Second Chapter of this <hi>Epiſtle</hi> a delineation and moſt <hi>prophetically,</hi> and at greateſt advantage after the mention of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> it is given.</p>
            <p n="5">5. His Third Chapfer moſt plainly and exprſly refers to <hi>Time;</hi> for he anſwers not as ſome think, the <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> but the <hi>Antichriſtians</hi> Objection, thoſe great <hi>Burleſquers</hi> of Chriſtianity into Fables; called therefore Scoffers; who ſay, That all things from the <hi>Flood</hi> having continued as they were, there is no ſuch change as of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> to be expected; and ſo all that which concerns the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> hath paſſed with them for <hi>Millenarian Hereſie.</hi> The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> hath therefore laid down the Rule and Standard of Time, accounting the Six-days of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, each as at a Thouſand Years; and in the Evening, or as between the two Evenings of the ſixth <hi>Millenary</hi> begins the <hi>Sabbatical Milenary,</hi> or the <hi>Seventh Thouſand;</hi> which is with the <hi>Lord;</hi> that is, with relation to the Lord, or the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, in relation to his <hi>Kingdom;</hi> but as one day, often cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Day of Judgment,</hi> and that <hi>Sabbath Day;</hi> in which Saying of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> That a <hi>Thouſand Years is as one Day;</hi> there is a manifeſt foreſight of the Divine Spirit, what it would make known by <hi>John,</hi> even that number'd, exactly Numbered Time of a <hi>Thouſand years;</hi> which the <hi>Apoſtle Peter</hi> affirm'd to be with the Lord, <hi>viz.</hi> as Time deſigned, and ſet out to the Lord as <hi>his own Times That one Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now as this view of this Epiſtle gives us a clear apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, how full to the purpoſe of <hi>Prophetical Scripture,</hi> this Epiſtle is written, how it ſimpathizes, and is contemporate with the whole Scope and Spirit of it; ſo the Words and Senſe of <hi>Interpretation</hi> is exactly fitted to all, and no other can fit it.</p>
            <p>For there were two things, all the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> both unbelieving, and believers, were fully agreed in.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the <hi>Prophecies</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> were of <hi>Divine Inſpiratien;</hi> that <hi>Prophecy</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> came not by the <hi>will of man,</hi> but was from the <hi>Holy Spirit:</hi> This the Believing, and Unbelieving <hi>Jews</hi> were both moſt zealous of.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:171163:8"/>
            <p n="2"> 2. That <hi>Meſſiah</hi> had a <hi>Kingdom</hi> aſſured to him in the <hi>Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies</hi> of <hi>Scripture:</hi> This even the Unbelieving <hi>Jews</hi> were all in higheſt expectation of at that very time; and the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving <hi>Jews</hi> alſo were earneſtly at that time in expectation of.</p>
            <p>To theſe the Apoſtle therefore cannot be ſuppoſed to direct the force of his Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>But that Jeſus Chriſt was not to be owned as the true <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah,</hi> the <hi>Son of God,</hi> and the <hi>King of Iſrael;</hi> notwithſtanding his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom did not immediately appear; was a Point the Unbelieving <hi>Jews</hi> are to this day ſcandalized at, even to their rejection of Chriſt the <hi>True Meſſiah;</hi> and the Chriſtian <hi>Hebrews</hi> were very tender in. Therefore that Jeſus Chriſt was the <hi>True Meſſiah,</hi> and that great Prince, the Apoſtle gave firſt the proof of the <hi>Transfiguration,</hi> as hath been ſhewn: And that he with <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John</hi> were Eye and Ear-Witneſſes; Three Witneſſes; in the Mouths of whom it was eſtabliſh'd, and no <hi>Cunningly deviſed Fable,</hi> to ſhift off the Scandal of the mean Appearance of our Lord, in the days of his <hi>Fleſh.</hi> But, ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>We have a more ſure word of Prophecy,</hi> as hath been opened; to which you <hi>do well to take heed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Objection ſtill remains; That the <hi>Prophecys</hi> run all upon a <hi>Glorious Kingdom of Meſſiah</hi> at that time to appear, as the Unbelieving <hi>Jews</hi> thought; and therefore the <hi>Scribes, Phariſees, Chief-Prieſts, Elders,</hi> their whole Sanhedrim determin'd againſt him with a high hand, that he was a Deceiver. The aſſerting therefore the Divine <hi>Inſpiration</hi> of <hi>Prophecy</hi> could not be to the main purpoſe; but that it is not of <hi>Private Interpretation,</hi> but that ſerious Chriſtians may find the ſenſe and meaning of it, and that it is not within the Encloſure or Embaraſſe of any San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hedrim, Council, or Infallible Breaſt; This is indeed highly to the purpoſe; and that according to the Senſe and Meaning of the <hi>Divine Spirit</hi> in it; one part compared with another, by the Aſſiſtances of the ſame Spirit; it would appear, that as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi>'s Seventy Weeks brought down Time to its fulneſs, <hi>viz.</hi> at the <hi>Death, Reſurrection,</hi> and <hi>Aſcention of Chriſt,</hi> that a <hi>dark place,</hi> or Interval of delay and patience, for that Kingdom muſt needs be for a long ſpace, but that yet that all Takers heed to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy <hi>Prophecy</hi> leads through <hi>the dark place,</hi> with the Illuminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that Courſe of Time, and how long it ſhall be until the <hi>dawning of the day, and the ſhining of the day Star</hi> into the hearts of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:171163:8"/> all his Saints, by the glorious appearance of Chriſt, and in the fulneſs of times, or all Times.</p>
            <p>Now all this is very evidently to a great and admirable end, purpoſe and effect in the Apoſtle's Diſcourſe in this Context and whole Epiſtle, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſettle the hearts of the Believing <hi>Hebrews,</hi> and of all Chriſtians in the comfortable Expectations of that <hi>Kingdom,</hi> in the midſt of the greateſt Darkneſs of the worſt Times; and it is with the greateſt Wiſdom of the <hi>Divine Spirit</hi> of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> that at this very Advantage the Apoſtle goes on to ſet out this Apoſtacy, at this very Joint of Diſcourſe of the <hi>dark place,</hi> which that very <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> was to create; and at naming of <hi>prophecy;</hi> and tells them, that there ſhall be falſe Prophets among <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> as there were among the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old: (So the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> in the <hi>Revelations</hi> joins the <hi>Antichriſtian Beaſt,</hi> and <hi>Falſe Prophet)</hi> in ſeveral Particulars oppoſite to the Apoſtles Doctrine, concerning <hi>Prophecy</hi> and <hi>Interpretation</hi> of Scripture, wherein they have <hi>Antichriſtianiz'd,</hi> as the <hi>Phariſes</hi> at that time had Prevaricated.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In that inſolent Pretence to <hi>Infallibility</hi> of <hi>Interpretation</hi> by a <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Council;</hi> and their <hi>Clergy</hi> would engroſs <hi>Interpretation,</hi> and the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Interpreting Scripture,</hi> as their own Propriety, Right and Dominion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In their Locking up Scripture from the people, under this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Pretence; They cannot interpret, nor have right to interpret it; ſo they cannot <hi>attend to the ſure word of prophecy,</hi> as they are commended here for doing.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In their peculiar Enmity to the ſearching the <hi>Prophecy</hi> of Scripture, and denying even to the moſt Learned to intermed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with it, ſeeing their own Condemnation in it; contrary to the Apoſtle's moſt peculiar Commendation of thoſe, who give heed to Prophecy.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In their ſetting up <hi>Tradition,</hi> a thing dependent wholly on Human Will above Scripture; whereas the Apoſtle commends Scripture and its <hi>Prophecy,</hi> that it came not by the Will of man, but by the Spirit.</p>
            <p n="5">5. In their allowing to their own <hi>Votaries</hi> the Credit and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of their pretended <hi>Inſpirations</hi> above the Cloſe attendance to <hi>Scripture Prophecy,</hi> and its <hi>Interpretation;</hi> which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> hath here ſo recommended to every <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and without the leaſt ſignification of <hi>Inſpiration</hi> Given to All; and his plain making former <hi>Scripture</hi> the Teſt of All following.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:171163:9"/>
            <p n="6"> 6. By exalting their Fabulous <hi>Legendary Miracles</hi> above <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> or the <hi>Prophecies;</hi> notwithſtanding even to the <hi>Transfigura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> The Apoſtle prefers the <hi>ſure Word of Prophecy;</hi> Although That was no <hi>Cunning deviſed Fable,</hi> and of ſo great an Excellency; by which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſeems <hi>prophetically</hi> to Glance moſt ſeverely up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe <hi>Cunningly Deviſed Fables,</hi> that ſhould ariſe in the <hi>Chriſtian Profeſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. The <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> Foretelling thoſe <hi>Scoffers in the laſt days,</hi> who ſhould ſet up the <hi>Mock Fifth Monarchy;</hi> ſo earneſtly recommends the <hi>Words</hi> of the <hi>Prophets,</hi> and the <hi>Commandments</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Saviour,</hi> the Great <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> and <hi>Jeſus;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he hath alſo given a very damning Predictory Admonition of the Grand <hi>Antichriſtian Apoſtacy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in all theſe, it may be ſaid to thoſe <hi>Antichriſtians,</hi> as it was to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and their <hi>Rulers</hi> of old; while they read theſe <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and the <hi>Prophecys</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> in their own way, they not underſtanding the Voices of the <hi>Prophets,</hi> are moſt juſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned in <hi>fulfilling</hi> them. For thus ought the <hi>Antichriſtian A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtacy</hi> to do, though moſt wickedly they do ſo, that theſe <hi>Scripture Prophecys</hi> may be <hi>fulfilled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All that hath now been ſpoken being by way of <hi>premiſal</hi> and <hi>preparation,</hi> I lay down theſe <hi>Propoſitions;</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That <hi>Scripture Prophecy</hi> is given by God, for a Light that muſt ſhine in the dark place of the <hi>Antichriſtian Apoſtacy,</hi> till the end of which the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is in delay.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Chriſtians do well to take heed to it as ſo ſhining, and giving the time, when the day of that <hi>Kingdom ſhall dawn,</hi> and the day Star of it ſhine into the hearts of all Saints.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Such heed cannot be given, except there be a Right gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to Chriſtians, and a power of interpreting <hi>Scripture Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. It is a Firſt Principle to Chriſtians, of the Apoſtle's ſetting and fixing, that all and every <hi>Prophecy</hi> of <hi>Scripture,</hi> and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly of Time relating to the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> is O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen and Free, and not a Private Record, or of any way an Enclos'd, Impropriated, or Appropriated Interpretation.</p>
            <p>For the more clear and illuſtrious arguing the Grand Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; That all, and every <hi>Prophecy</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> is not of a <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:171163:9"/> or <hi>ſecret,</hi> but of an open, free, and publick <hi>Interpretation;</hi> I will firſt proceed by direct and down right proof and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, that of all <hi>Scripture,</hi> except that which lays down the Truths, preciſely, and abſolutely neceſſary to Salvarion: <hi>The Prophecy of Scripture is in its Interpretation, moſt Free, open,</hi> and moſt <hi>certain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will in the ſecond place give Anſwers to the great Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt this Propoſition ſo prov'd.</p>
            <p>I will in the Third Place conſider what Standards according to Reaſon and Scripture-underſtanding may be given, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we may judge whether any one hath given a true <hi>Interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of <hi>Scripture Prophecy, viz.</hi> whereby the perſon giving ſuch true <hi>Interpretation,</hi> and whereby Any other may judge of it, and find it ſo.</p>
            <p>In the Fourth Place, I will draw out in moſt publick view, the Evidences I my ſelf have within my ſelf, and have offered to others, that I have given a True Interpretation of <hi>Scripture Prophecy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this I will do with moſt particular relation to <hi>prophetical numbers</hi> of <hi>Time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will Super-add a Judgment upon the ſtate of Time Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medious from hence to the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt;</hi> and ſhew, that the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> ſhall be very ſudden, and as Lightning: And this I ſhall do by way of retractation, and correction of Any thing wherein I have err'd in this matter; and what will be as an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of an Objection, that Glories in the preſent appearance of Things to Senſe, as if no ſuch Kingdom were near.</p>
            <p>I will recollect the whole in ſome very Brief Reflections for the ſettlement of the Judgment and practice, in relation to <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Prophecy,</hi> concerning Time.</p>
            <p>I begin with the Firſt; The arguing the Propoſition, which ſhall inſiſt upon theſe Four Heads, or Topicks.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I argue from the Infinite Ability of the Divine Spirit, ſo to give <hi>Prophecy,</hi> that the Interpretation may be Free and Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I argue from the neceſſity; That whatever is written with ſenſe, and coherence of the things written, and with the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Truth, if the parts of ſuch Diſcourſes are diligently compar'd, and ſagaciouſly intermedled with by perſons ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:171163:10"/> themſelves thereunto, a certain <hi>Interpretation</hi> muſt needs fly out to them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I argue from the gracious Aſſiſtances and Promiſes that the <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> will as the <hi>Spirit of Truth lead into all Truth, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing things that are to come;</hi> and give <hi>the key of knowledge,</hi> leading into the Sectets of Prophecy; even wherein our <hi>Dulneſs</hi> and <hi>Slowneſs of Heart</hi> makes them ſo, notwithſtanding the Proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Spirit for their <hi>Interpretation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argument</hi> I. The Divine Spirit hath an Infinite and Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Preſcience of things that are to come to paſs; <hi>Known to him are the Works of God from the very Foundation of the World</hi> to the end of it, with every particular Accident to the very leaſt Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance; and therefore he can foretell all things, as clearly as he pleaſes; and ſo that they may be interpreted and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood.</p>
            <p>He ſearcheth <hi>all things,</hi> even the <hi>deep things of God,</hi> whoſe <hi>Counſels of old are faithfulneſs and truth;</hi> who calleth the End from the Beginning, and can declare it; For he worketh all thingsaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Counſel of his own Will, which Will he <hi>knew from E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity</hi> within himſelf.</p>
            <p>This Preſcience of the Divine Spirit is acknowledg'd by All Chriſtians, except ſome few who leaſt deſerve the Name of Chriſtians, who deny the Actual Determinations of Free, or what we call Fortuitous Agents, to be <hi>Scibilia,</hi> or Knowable.</p>
            <p>I make not therefore here any diſpute concerning the High Myſtery of the Supreme Preſcience; how, or in what manner God foreknew, when the things fore known depend on cauſes acting ſo freely, that what they will chooſe, ſeems impoſſible to be known before hand; or ſo fortuitouſly, that if it could be foreſeen how they would be caſt, the Fortuitouſneſs ſeems de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed: But that God does foreknow, I take for granted, even as it is much the more generally agreed; and in ſeveral greateſt Inſtances of each kind, it is moſt evident and undeniable in Scripture, God hath foretold the Events of each ſort; God mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies his own Divinity; and challenges all Falſe Names of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity upon this very Point: For thus he ſays, <hi>Declare to us things to come, that we may know you are Gods,</hi> Iſa. 43. 23. And as he foreſees, and fore-knows with infinite clearneſs and perſpicuity; even ſo he is able, according to the nature of <hi>Prophetick Language,</hi> which he hath conſtituted and fram'd, taking the Example from none, but giving it to all.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:171163:10"/>
            <p>—to Expreſs all things Prophetically.</p>
            <p>He employs the true Laws of ſpeaking Prophetically, and <hi>ſhewing things to come;</hi> he knows by his own Wiſdom, ſo to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern the ſpeaking of his Servants the <hi>Prophets,</hi> that <hi>prophetical things may be compar'd with prophetical: Prophetical things in the Old-Teſtament, with prophetical things in the New:</hi> Even as he hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken care in all Spiritual Things in General, as the Apoſtle ſhews at large, 1 <hi>Cor. c.</hi> 2. That they may be ſo expreſs'd, that Spiritual things may be compar'd with Spiritual; Even ſo that <hi>Prophetical Emblems, Figures, Iconiſms, Types, Numbers of Time</hi> in the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New-Teſtament</hi> may be compar'd and co-ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted one with another; that They as face to face, or as Tally to Tally may anſwer and agree, the one to the other; and may not be of any ſuch private Interpretation, as not to be ſearch'd into, or underſtood. He alſo foreſaw there would be, and took care there ſhould be Monuments of clear, undoubted, and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Hiſtory, to correſpond with <hi>Prophecy,</hi> as Teſtimonies of a mighty and powerful providence, that ſhould ratifie it by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent; and that there ſhould be among all Nations in their <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorical Records</hi> witneſſes thereunto.</p>
            <p>Nay, beyond this, by the Infiniteneſs of the Divine Foreſight, the <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> hath choſen out ſuch Words, as ſhould themſelves give great Light and Confirmation in the Explanation of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy by their own Light; by falling in with the Words, made uſe of in the time of Events coming to paſs. For the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit</hi> having a certain Foreſight of the Words that ſhould be at any time in general uſe, could point to them many Ages be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, for his own ſervice in <hi>Prophecy;</hi> and being ſo pointed to, and coming ſo into uſe, they make a very conſiderable Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter to diſtinguiſh both Times, and their juſt place in <hi>Prophecy.</hi> In the ſame manner the <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> foreknew, what celebrated Rule or Number there would be found neceſſary in any Age for the Adjuſtment and Menſuration of time to ſuch purpoſes, as he had to remark upon in his <hi>Prophetical</hi> Frame; and when he is pleas'd to make any Alluſion to it, it is of ſingular uſe to the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication and aſſurance of <hi>Prophetical Time,</hi> and whereabout in Time we are, by concerting one with another, <hi>viz.</hi> One ſuch Note in <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> and Event with ſuch its correſpondent Note in <hi>Prophecy;</hi> many particulars in each ſort of theſe ſhall after be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marked, and they'll plainly ſhew, that <hi>Prophecy</hi> was not inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, nor deſign'd for ſecrecy, and reſerve from All <hi>Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:171163:11"/>
            <p>Now in all theſe Particulars I uſe the Word Foreknew, or Foreſaw; to avoid any diſpute on the Word Fore-ordered, which elſe I altogether prefer.</p>
            <p>God therefore in ſcorn to the Dark <hi>Oracles</hi> of the Devil, as well as to the Black Dens and Caves, out of which he gave them, ſays thus; <hi>Eſay</hi> 45. 19. <hi>I have not ſpoken in ſecret, in a dark place of the earth; I ſaid not unto the ſeed of Jacob, ſeek ye my face in vain, viz.</hi> my Counſel and Will in <hi>Prophecy,</hi> as they that ſeek to the <hi>Idols</hi> of the <hi>Heathen; For I the Lord ſpeak Righteouſneſs, I declare the things that are Right; Right</hi> in Regard of Infinite Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and Fore-knowledg of all Events; I ſpeak Things <hi>That are All plain to him that <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandeth, and Right to them that find Knowledg.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It cannot be ſupoſed, that the Divine Spirit can have any neceſſity upon him to ſpeak Darkly, or Ambiguouſly concerning things to come, if he pleaſe to ſpeak at all of them; as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly he hath been pleaſed to ſpeak of them; or that in that Regard <hi>Prophecy</hi> of Scripture ſhould be of any reſerv'd, or ſecret <hi>Interpretation;</hi> For all things, however to come, are ſo <hi>Open</hi> and <hi>Naked</hi> before him, with whom we have to do, that he need not <hi>Darken Counſel by words without Knowledg, either, as they do, who know not Themſelves,</hi> nor <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand;</hi> and ſo cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get Knowledg in others; Or that would deceive; For he knows All, ſo as to ſpeak plainly, clearly, certainly, concerning Them; He underſtands them fully, the certainty of their coming to paſs: He is neither Neſcient, nor Doubtful concerning any Thing, or the Manner, or the Time of its comming to paſs; and therefore, how long ſoever he ſpeaks of them before hand, yet he needs not ſo to ſpeak, as to hide himſelf in his <hi>Prophecy</hi> concerning Them, or ſeek Subter-fuges, or Ambi Dextrous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions concerning Them any more, nor ſo much as any Other He, that looks moſt downright on things preſent; For as <hi>Darkneſs</hi> and <hi>Light</hi> are <hi>all one to the Father of Lights,</hi> ſo <hi>Yeſterday</hi> and <hi>to Day</hi> are all one to him, who <hi>Inhabits Eternity,</hi> and <hi>who is without any Variation,</hi> or <hi>Shaddow of Turning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All theſe Things are ſo undoubtedly certain, ſo Univerſally Agreed, and Acknowledg'd, that altho they themſelves make a High Argument in this point; yet They need no Proof, but Require only to be Magnified, Diſplayed, and Illuſtrated.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argum.</hi> 2. Any Author, or Writer that can Write Senſe, and who does indeed Write Senſe, and Writes with ſome
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:171163:11"/> Largeneſs, and Diffuſiveneſs of that his Senſe, and does declare He would be Heard, and Read; and would have the Minds that have Wiſdom, Exerciſe themſelves upon what is Written; let him wrap up his Mind, and Senſe in ſuch Figures, that none but the Wiſe, and Conſidering ſhould find out his mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and let it but be, that he accordingly hath Framed his Diſcourſe; whenever ſuch a Writer gives out, and makes publick ſuch a Writing; he thereby puts it under the Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of every One, that is Wiſe and Sagacious, and who will allow the Time, and Thought, that is neceſſary to make ſuch Obſervation and Compare of the Hints, and Remarks that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be Avoided in Rational and Coherent Diſcourſe; however Involv'd in Symbols and Figures; by which the Senſe and Meaning may be Underſtood, and Found out.</p>
            <p>But now it is on one ſide moſt True, that None, as the Divine Spirit can Write Higheſt Truth, and of Stupendious Signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cancy, and Coherence; and yet Veil, and Hide it ſo, as that it ſhould be impoſſible to find it out, but remain perfect <hi>Myſtery,</hi> till the time of Revealing it ſhould come; if he pleaſed ſo to have it; But then on the other hand, none, as he can Write in Figures, and under Veils, and yet ſo mix the Lights, and the Shades, if he pleaſe to have it ſo; that the <hi>Minds,</hi> that <hi>have Wiſdom</hi> ſhall find Light Ariſing, and Springing out in <hi>Taking heed to the ſure Word of Prophecy:</hi> And if They are Inclin'd and ſtirr'd up, <hi>to ſeparate Themſelves to Intermiddle with this Wiſdom,</hi> it cannot be, but they muſt make great Diſcoveries; If they faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully attend and lay the parts one to another, and it be the will of that <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> they ſhould do ſo.</p>
            <p>Now that it is his Pleaſure, They ſhould do ſo, is made known by the very Writing, and Publication of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> and no Prohibition of Searching it; as alſo by the obligation, that lies upon all, when he Writes to obſerve, and underſtand. (This is due in Meaſure to every Intelligent, and Worthy Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but without Meaſure to his, the Spirits Writing) It is known to be his pleaſure; Becauſe there is a General Command to <hi>Search the Scripture;</hi> Becauſe <hi>All Scripture</hi> is given by <hi>Inſpiration of God,</hi> and is <hi>Profitable,</hi> and there is no Interdict upon <hi>Prophecy</hi> as to the ſearch, nor Limitation, as to the Profitableneſs; It is known to be his pleaſure concerning <hi>Prophecy,</hi> becauſe it is ſaid by our Lord with Relation to the <hi>Prophecy</hi> of <hi>Daniel; Let him that read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand;</hi> Becauſe the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> hath ſaid of the <hi>more ſure word of Prophecy, yee do well in Taking heed to it; becauſe it is</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:171163:12"/> 
               <hi>written,</hi> as in Golden Letters on the Portal of the <hi>Revelation; Bleſſed is he that Readeth, and they that hear the words of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy of this Book;</hi> which muſt needs imply with Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; Becauſe it is the <hi>Epiphonema,</hi> the Burden of every Epiſtle of it; <hi>He that hath an Ear, let him hear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if it be thus, then all the Locking up the Mind of the <hi>Holy Spirit of Prophecy</hi> is, that he may reſerve the Secrets of it for the peculiar Friends (I ſay not of his <hi>word</hi> in general) but of his <hi>Prophetick Word;</hi> and that they may whet up the ſharpeſt Exerciſe of their Powers of Underſtanding to find the Golden Taches, and Couplings; and one Part of <hi>Prophecy</hi> may be joyn'd to Another, and the whole peice be under view in all its Frame, and Contexture.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as ever therefore, the Holy Spirit hath once Publiſh'd, and Expos'd his <hi>Prophetic</hi> Writings, and thereby, and therein Affix'd them to the <hi>Pillars</hi> of the <hi>Temple;</hi> They are by his Grace made the Right of his Servants to ſearch into, and to Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand; For they then ceaſe to be the <hi>Secret Things</hi> that <hi>Belong to God;</hi> But they being <hi>Reveal'd,</hi> become thoſe that <hi>Belong to us, and to our Children;</hi> we enter into that Priviledg of the <hi>Iſrael of God, To us belong the Oracles of God;</hi> every ſervant of God, that hath his <hi>Heart ſtirred up,</hi> hath very good Right to ſearch, and his ſearch is no Sacriledg, nor ſhall be imputed to him, as Curioſity, or preſumption; It is his Right to Search, even as among Men, it is no Violation to Inquire into the Senſe of any Author, offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf to the Publick; and there is greater Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in <hi>Searching the ſure Word of Prophecy</hi> than in Searching any other Author, or Writing, as is next to be ſpoken.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argum.</hi> 3. I Argue from the Infinite Grace of the Divine Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that as he hath Given to Man a ſearching Mind after all Knowledg, ſo he would not give any part of Scripture, as a Torment of wiſe Inquiſitive Perſons, but give the <hi>Key</hi> of <hi>Knowledg</hi> to Them; and that he will, as the <hi>Spirit of Truth ſo Lead into All Truth, and ſhew his Servants Things to Come,</hi> with ſuch Uprightneſs, Faithfulneſs, and Sincerity; that there ſhall be no more Secreſy, or privacy in the Interpretation of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> than is neceſſary according to the Laws, He knows Juſt, and Due; and which he hath himſelf weigh'd out, as ſo Juſt, and Due to <hi>Prophetick Oracles;</hi> even as in All other parts of Scripture, he hath in Infinite Wiſdom, <hi>as he weighed out the Mountains in Scales,</hi> and <hi>the HIlls in a Ballance,</hi> ſo proportion'd to every point of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:171163:12"/> Scripture-Truth its Exact meaſure of clearneſs of <hi>Revelation,</hi> and ſo conſequently of <hi>Interpretation;</hi> the moſt neceſſary are the moſt plain; and yet there are Truths of the Grace of God freely <hi>Juſtifying,</hi> and Accepting ſinners in Chriſt, that call for the moſt Quicken'd, and Awaken'd Faculties, for the <hi>Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> of them; as alſo concerning the inward Operations of the Grace of God in the Hearts of Men; and yet in all Theſe, and ſuch as Theſe, <hi>The Holy Spirit</hi> hath Wiſely, and Holyly Given out his Oracles in a moſt Righteous Scale, between the Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of the Truth he Reveals, and the Exerciſe he knows ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to the Mind of Man in Searching out the <hi>Interpretation;</hi> and ſo hath made the Manifeſtation more Ligtſome, or Requir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Cloſer Attendance; And thus in <hi>Prophecy</hi> according to the Vehemency of Search and Enquiry he hath thought fit, he hath Diſpenſed. This doth not make it yet <hi>Private Interpretation;</hi> becauſe there are ſuch Lines of Communication between part, and part, <hi>Emblem</hi> and <hi>Emblem, number</hi> of <hi>Time,</hi> and <hi>number</hi> of <hi>Time;</hi> between words in <hi>Prophecy,</hi> and words uſed in the <hi>Time</hi> of <hi>Prophecy</hi> Fullfill'd; between Rules of Time in <hi>Prophecy</hi> and cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated Rules of Time among Men in <hi>Prophecy</hi> Fulfill'd; between <hi>Prophecy,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Hiſtory,</hi> that all may be made Plain.</p>
            <p>But beyond All this, <hi>Interpretation</hi> of <hi>Prophecy</hi> is not <hi>Private,</hi> becauſe <hi>The Spirit of Prophecy,</hi> who Knowes it, becauſe he gave it; Even that <hi>Bleſſed Publick Spirit of Wiſdom, Truth, Scripture, is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to Aſſiſt his Servants,</hi> Searching into <hi>Prophecy;</hi> Leading them into the <hi>Treaſures</hi> of it; Springing Thoughts into them all of the Sudden; <hi>Bringing</hi> Things to their <hi>Remembrance,</hi> that elſe would not have come there; and ſo Enabling them to Match, and Enterweave All thoſe Foremention'd Indentings one with another; and thereby raiſing in them Aſſurances, equal to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration.</p>
            <p>He alſo foreſaw, what Humble Enquirers into theſe Things he would ſtir up and Aſſiſt in every Time, and what meaſures of Aſſiſtance he would Allow them; And yet, this does not make <hi>Interpretation Private</hi> to ſuch perſons apart, becauſe ſuch Acceſſes to All the Means of Interpretation, and to thoſe Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances of the Spirit are free and open to one, as well as another; and what is given in <hi>Interpretation</hi> to any one, ought to be freely Communicated, and in the Reaſons and Grounds of it, It lies open to All: And they who are thus Aſſiſted, are not Aſſiſted for Themſelves only, but as <hi>Lights ſet on an hill,</hi> that they may not be <hi>Hid.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:171163:13"/>
            <p>Now this Aſſiſtance of that Bleſſed Spirit, as a Spirit Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly preſent to the <hi>Searchers</hi> into <hi>Prophecy,</hi> is an Encouragement beyond what any Author in the World can give to them, who ſearch into their Writings; For who as he, can be ſo always preſent to the Minds, and Underſtandings of Thoſe, who Read, and Meditate upon them? Who, as he can Recompenſe the Love Reverence and Diligence of thoſe, who wait upon Him? Who can, as he Prompt to Them, ſummon to their Memory; keep them in Doubt, and ſo urge them to further Enquiries, refreſh their Reſearches, and ſo make Things fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther known to Them? ſo ſettle, confirm, and aſſure Them, that they may know the Certainty of the Words of Truth?</p>
            <p>This is an undeniable Priviledg, and Ground of Hope to All, who ſet Themſelves by Prayer, Deſire and Humble En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to Search, and ſo ſeek out the Miſteries of Wiſdom to be found out in the <hi>Book of Prophecy;</hi> why then ſhould it be Thought a Hopeleſs Undertaking, or an <hi>Incredible Thing</hi> that any one ſhould be ſo Aſſiſted, that doth Humbly Profeſs, he hath ſo waited upon God in his Word? Or that <hi>That Key of Prophetical Knowledg</hi> ſhould be vouchſafed to ſuch a one, when ſo gracious Aſſiſtances are Promiſed from and by the Divine Spirit, the <hi>Publick Spirit of Prophecy,</hi> and its <hi>Interpretation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now All this I have Diſcourſed in General, I would parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly Argue concerning <hi>Prophetick Time,</hi> and by an Argument moſt peculiar to it:</p>
            <p>For not only in general, If <hi>All and Every Prophecy</hi> be Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted of a not <hi>private Interpretation,</hi> then not <hi>Prophecies</hi> by Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers defining Time to the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt;</hi> For as hath been ſaid, if <hi>All Scripture,</hi> as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſays, be of <hi>Divine Inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> Then <hi>Prophecy;</hi> So if All <hi>Prophecy</hi> be not of <hi>Private Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> then not that very particular Part of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> which Defines Time; And as <hi>Prophecy</hi> is ſo excellent a part of <hi>Scripture,</hi> ſo the Numbers Defining Time are an excellent part of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> and therefore cannot be of <hi>private Interpretation,</hi> if Prophecy be not ſo; For every General includes all, eſpecially chiefeſt Particulars.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall further Argue with a Peculiar Reſpect to the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetick Numbers of Time,</hi> that they of any cannot be of <hi>Private Interpretation;</hi> For <hi>Number, Weight</hi> and <hi>Meaſure</hi> are Things of ſo great Exactneſs, that the whole Communication of the World Depends upon them; and Scripture puts upon them great Honour alſo, requiring above all, that they be Exact;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:171163:13"/> as the Rules of all Enter-Courſe; Now therefore when Scripture takes <hi>Number</hi> and <hi>Meaſures</hi> of Time into it ſelf; if theſe are not well underſtood, how can they be ſuch Standards of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-courſe? Seeing then Prophecy hath ſo many Numbers 2300 <hi>Eves, Morns; Time, Times, Half a Time;</hi> 1290 <hi>Days;</hi> 1335 <hi>Days</hi> in <hi>Daniel;</hi> 1260 <hi>Days</hi> with <hi>Time, Times, Half a Time, Three Days</hi> and an <hi>Half;</hi> and 42 <hi>Months</hi> 2 <hi>Times</hi> mentioned in the <hi>Revel.</hi> if theſe Numbers, that ſo evidently ſpeak a Fitneſs for Calculation of Time with greateſt Exactneſs; If theſe by a due Search and Compare one with another cannot be underſtood; what ſpaces of Time they Define, when they begin, and when they End; They of all the Points of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> tho they carry the Face, and Appearance of Greateſt Significancy, yet would be indeed of all the moſt Inſignificant. Now ſeeing an Inſignificancy in the Higheſt Points of Signification can by no means be imputed to the Wiſe, and <hi>Holy Spirit of Prophecy;</hi> I conclude, that even theſe <hi>Prophetick Numbers</hi> in a peculiar, and Eminent Manner, may be underſtood, both what ſpace of Time they Emenſurate, or Line out to us, and alſo when they Begin, and when they End; and ſo I have finiſhed the Firſt Head of Diſcourſe I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed.</p>
            <p>I come now therefore to the Second Head propoſed, to give Anſwers to the great Objections, that are Levyed againſt this Propoſition, <hi>viz.</hi> That All, and every <hi>Prophecy of Scripture</hi> is not of <hi>Private,</hi> or <hi>Reſerv'd,</hi> but Publick, Free and open <hi>Interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 1. If <hi>Prophecy of Scripture</hi> be of ſo Free, Publick and Unreſerv'd <hi>Interpretation,</hi> how comes it to paſs, that ſo few have ſo much, as Attempted the Books of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> that Fore-tell Great Events, and the Times of Them? Yea, that Moſt judg it ſo Unpreſumable and Undertaking, as to Reject all <hi>Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Daniel,</hi> and the <hi>Revelation,</hi> that Debate Things through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to their utmoſt point and iſſue; and that ſearch what, or what manner of Time is ſignified by the Spirit in them; or is more, than by way of ordinary Comment; as if they were the Performances of only Fanatical, and Imaginative Men; and upon the Evidence but of ſuch an Endeavour, condemn them immediately as ſuch.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:171163:14"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Let God be True, and every Man a Lyar;</hi> Now God hath ſaid <hi>Every Prophecy of Scripture</hi> is ſo Deſcended, that it is not of <hi>Private Interpretation;</hi> that <hi>they do well,</hi> who attend to the Light of it, <hi>ſhining as in a Dark place,</hi> and ſo Enlightning it; if then it were Dark it ſelf, how ſhould it enlighten a <hi>Dark Place;</hi> for it would be Dark to Dark, which increaſes Darkneſs ſtill; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever enlightens, muſt be it ſelf Light. This main Truth ought therefore at all times to remain Stable, and Firm.</p>
            <p>The immediate Cauſe therefore of this ſo general prejudice againſt ſearch into <hi>Prophecy,</hi> however Coloured over with Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty and Reverence of Divine Myſteries, and ſecrets, into which Men pretend they would not Pry, are theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There is ſo great a Darkneſs upon the preſent ſtate, that though the <hi>Light Shines</hi> in it, yet it, as <hi>Darkneſs, comprehends not the Light of Prophecy ſhining</hi> upon it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hence, as Men in the <hi>Dark,</hi> they are Afraid of every ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of Difficulty; They ſay concerning All <hi>Interpretation of Prophecy, There is a Lyon in the way.</hi> It is as the Sons of <hi>Anak</hi> to them, that cannot be Encounter'd, and as the <hi>Walls</hi> that cannot be Scaled; ſo difficult and unintelligible is <hi>Prophecy,</hi> that it cannot be <hi>Interpreted;</hi> It is as a <hi>Sealed Book,</hi> the Learned cannot Read, becauſe Sealed; nor the unlearned, becauſe not <hi>Learned:</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. How many are they, who are afraid of the very Light it ſelf? what <hi>Prophecy</hi> Reveals, is ſo contrary to the State they are in, that they are, as the Expreſſion is in <hi>Job,</hi> upon all appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of ſuch <hi>Light,</hi> as it were in the <hi>Terrors of the ſhaddow of Death;</hi> The Aſpect of <hi>Prophecy</hi> upon both the Civil and Eccleſiaſtick State of the preſent World is moſt Terrible, eſpecially, when it comes to the Determination of Time, as near: Thus the Lord makes Fooliſh the Wiſdom of the Wiſe, <hi>&amp;c. Eſay</hi> 28. that they cannot endure it, and <hi>ſo hate the Light,</hi> and will not come to it, leaſt their State ſhould be Reproved and Shaken; and are An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, that ſuch a Light ſhould be flaſhed in their Faces.</p>
            <p>But theſe are only the next, or ſecond Cauſes, there is a high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er judiciary Cauſe, that ſways Righteouſly, and Holily; and yet ſo, as <hi>Permitting,</hi> and leaving Men to themſelves; even this; That Becauſe men do not like to <hi>attend to the ſure Word of Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> God gives them up to this Culpable Cauſe, and Reaſon, of all the <hi>Injudiciouſneſſes</hi> concerning the <hi>meaning of Prophecy</hi> and <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Prepoſſeſſions againſt the <hi>Interpretation</hi> of it, as if it were pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, and Reſerv'd; and thus that his Wiſe, and Juſt purpoſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:171163:14"/> purpoſe ſhould be fulfilled; that <hi>the dark place</hi> ſhould be a <hi>dark place ſtill,</hi> while <hi>the Apoſtacy</hi> ſhould, according to <hi>the Oath of Chriſt for Time, Times and half Time</hi> continue; and till <hi>the Day down,</hi> and <hi>the Day-Star ariſe in mens hearts;</hi> and yet <hi>no Encouragement, or Boldneſs</hi> miniſtred to it, that it might continue ſo <hi>Dark</hi> without Great Sin. And indeed, though the faulty Cauſe of all this be the <hi>not Receiving the Truth in the Love of it;</hi> (on which God gives up the <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> to <hi>ſtrong Deluſions, and to believe a Lye;)</hi> and becauſe of <hi>the Few,</hi> and <hi>Small Things</hi> he hath againſt his <hi>Suffering Churches</hi> of <hi>Pergamus</hi> and <hi>Thyatyra;</hi> and the <hi>Sardian</hi> State of <hi>the Reformation,</hi> that <hi>hath a Name to Live,</hi> and yet <hi>is dead;</hi> Upon all theſe Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts <hi>Prophccy</hi> is ſo little underſtood; ſaying the Glimmerings of Light given by a very Few, and thoſe very Little Accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Interpreters, that do inlighten, and ſhew by a Little, how this <hi>dark place</hi> would be inlightned by <hi>taking heed to the Sure Word of Prophecy.</hi> But I am about to ſay, if <hi>Prophecy</hi> were as Fully and Truly <hi>Interpreted,</hi> as the Publickneſs of its <hi>Conſtitution</hi> for <hi>Interpretation,</hi> would give Leave to; it would eſpecially now ſo near the End, ſo inlighten <hi>the dark place,</hi> that there would be no <hi>Room found</hi> for the <hi>Darkneſs of the Apoſtacy,</hi> but it <hi>would fly away</hi> like <hi>Shades of the Night</hi> at the Morning Appearance. But as the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>God hath concluded All under Sin,</hi> ſo under <hi>the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy,</hi> either in Full, as in <hi>the Antichriſtian</hi> World; or in Part, as in <hi>the Reformation-Part,</hi> that in his own Time he might <hi>have mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy upon All.</hi> On <hi>the Heighth and Depth of the Riches</hi> of both the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Knowledge of God! How unſearchable are his paths, and his ways paſt finding out! For of him and by him are all things, to him be glory for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Diſagreement among the <hi>Interpreters of Prophecy,</hi> and more particularly, the Great Miſtakes they have fallen into in point of Time, ſeems a more <hi>formidable Objection</hi> againſt the Freeneſs and Publickneſs of the <hi>Interpretation of Prophecy;</hi> and moſt as to Time; For when Wiſe, Learned, Sagacious, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Diligent, Zealous, and Holy Perſons have ſet themſelves to inquire, and find out the Mind of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and have not found it, but have diſagreed among themſelves; and ſo <hi>ſome</hi> muſt be in miſtakes; For they cannot differ, and all be in the Right; This is much more againſt <hi>the Interpretation of Prophecy,</hi> being not <hi>private,</hi> than if none had attempted: For were it not under Reſerve, why have they not been more ſucceſsful in find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that have ſo tryed, and put themſelves forth to the utmoſt therein.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:171163:15"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. We ought to be very wary to urge either Miſtakes or Differences of <hi>Interpreters,</hi> in <hi>interpreting Prophecy of Scripture,</hi> leſt we ſhut our ſelves out of all <hi>Interpretation of Scripture</hi> in Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral; yea, even out of Great Points of Faith, and Truth of the Goſpel; Becauſe in all theſe there are Great Differences of Explication; and therefore Miſtakes on ſome ſide: Should we therefore Reaſon, Theſe are ſo Dark and Reſerv'd as not to be medled with? This would be an high Diſhonour to our Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Profeſſion; Let us much rather make our Attendances to <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> and <hi>Meditation,</hi> more Inward, Conſtant, Serious, Deep, Humble, with more earneſt Supplications for Divine Aſſiſtance, and <hi>Free Communications</hi> of his Spirit, the Author of all Knowledg in the Truths making <hi>wiſe to Salvation,</hi> and ſo in <hi>Interpretation of Prophecy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. Whenſoever Any have fallen ſhort, or are miſtaken in the <hi>Interpretation of Prophecy,</hi> we muſt conclude there was a want of Due Attendance; and God Left even Good Men and his Servants ſo to themſelves, that they have miſs'd in what they have ſeem'd to themſelves, or even to others, to have attain'd. But in the mean time nothing is to be charg'd upon <hi>Prophecy of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> or <hi>the Nature</hi> and <hi>Conſtitution of it</hi> as to <hi>Interpretation;</hi> as if it were dark and incertain, and we could ne're be ſure whether we had it aright or not, ſo contrary to the Apoſtles Doctrine concerning it; For as no Weakneſs or Indiſpoſition of the Eye, or Diſadvantage in Avenues, or Entrances of Light, are to be charg'd on the Light it ſelf; ſo none of the <hi>Hallucinations,</hi> or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-ſights, or <hi>Stumbles of the Interpreters of Prophecy,</hi> are to be imputed ſo much to the <hi>Difficulty of Interpretation of it,</hi> as in it ſelf; but to our Dullneſs of ſight, or <hi>hearing,</hi> what <hi>the Spirit</hi> hath therein <hi>ſaid to the Churches.</hi> Nor is any one therefore to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged, but only cautioned, <hi>not to be high minded,</hi> but <hi>to fear;</hi> Even as the many Miſcarriages in perſons <hi>ſeeking Eternal Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> ſhould not deter us from walking in the <hi>way of Life,</hi> but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige us to do it with an <hi>holy fear and trembling,</hi> leſt we ſhould ſo much as <hi>ſeem to fall ſhort.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 3. It will be ſaid, It is true, Nothing is to be laid to the charge of <hi>Prophecy</hi> it ſelf, or to the <hi>Conſtitution of it</hi> for ſuch <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation,</hi> as God intended for it. But it may hence be collected, God intended <hi>Prophecies</hi> ſhould be kept ſecret, until either they ſhall be opened in ſuch a glorious ſtate of the Church, as is ſignified
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:171163:15"/> by the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> or till each <hi>Prophecy</hi> ſhall be fullfilled; or, at leaſt, till as near the <hi>Time of fullfilling,</hi> as it was when <hi>Daniel</hi> by <hi>Beoks underſtood</hi> concerning the End of the Seventy Years Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Nothing of what is mentioned in this <hi>Objection</hi> will ſatisfy what the <hi>Apoſtle Peter</hi> hath here affirmed; For that <hi>Prophecy</hi> ſhould be a <hi>Light ſhining in a dark place,</hi> can by no means be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated to the <hi>ſtate of the Kingdom of Chriſt:</hi> That could ne'r be ſtyl'd by the <hi>Apostle</hi> a <hi>dark place;</hi> although it is moſt True, <hi>Prophecy</hi> ſhall lye open, as a Volume, moſt clearly and fully un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, in the Hall (as I may ſay) of that Palace of the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom;</hi> but not as in a <hi>dark place,</hi> but as Light uniting with Light, unto perfect Brightneſs; Then it is the <hi>Day</hi> ſhall <hi>dawn,</hi> and the <hi>Day-ſtar ſhine</hi> in the very <hi>Hearts</hi> of all the Servants of Chriſt, and the <hi>Light of one Day be as the Light of ſeven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor can the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> ſenſe be made good by <hi>Prophecy</hi> being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, when fullfilled: For indeed the Diſputes are as Great concerning the Time, at which <hi>Prophecies,</hi> that undoubtedly have been long ago <hi>fullfilled,</hi> were fullfilled as concerning <hi>Prophecies</hi> yet to be <hi>fullfilled.</hi> And though it may well be allowed, that there have been ſome Bruits and Noiſes of the Things foretold by <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy,</hi> that they were coming to paſs at the time they did come to paſs; yet there are Two Things evidently intended by the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> as the Great Scope and End of his Diſcourſe, much to be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by all that would find the Purpoſe of the Holy Spirit by him.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That there is one <hi>Glorious Day,</hi> and <hi>Day-Star</hi> to break out and <hi>ſhine in the World;</hi> which is the Great Point at which <hi>Prophecy</hi> aims, and into which it ſhall unite, as a Leſſer <hi>Light</hi> with a Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and <hi>more Glorious:</hi> which is indeed the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> and to which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> had reſpect, as is to be ſhewn throughout this <hi>Epiſtle.</hi> This is that Time of the <hi>Reſtitution of All Things,</hi> of which all the <hi>Prophets</hi> have ſpoken, <hi>ſince the World began,</hi> as that ſame <hi>Apoſtle Peter</hi> ſpoke, <hi>Acts</hi> 3. 21. This is the <hi>Mpſtery to be fulfilled,</hi> as he hath ſpoken, or <hi>Evangelized,</hi> as Happieſt Tydings, by <hi>All his Sevants the Prophets:</hi> Rev. 10. 7. <hi>Prophecy</hi> is therefore a <hi>Light ſhining</hi> till then, and guiding to the Time when it is to begin, and then falls in One with it, as the forenam'd Scriptures ſhew.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:171163:16"/>
            <p n="2"> 2. There is a very particular <hi>dark place,</hi> that <hi>Prophecy ſhines</hi> as a <hi>Light</hi> in, till then; and it is indeed the whole Time from the <hi>Delay of the Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> at his <hi>Reſurrestion</hi> and <hi>Aſcenſion,</hi> till it <hi>dawns</hi> and <hi>riſes</hi> as a <hi>Day-ſtar;</hi> but it is yet more particularly the Time and State of the <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> which is as a <hi>Smoak darkning the Air,</hi> even the whole State of Chriſtianity in the very <hi>Heavens of it. Prophecy</hi> ſhines therefore as a <hi>Light in a dark place,</hi> giving Aſſurance of, and ſhewing the Time of that Day; and <hi>Day-Star dawning</hi> upon the World; till it ſhall Illuminate into the very Heart, with its mighty Influences and Beams of Glory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 4. It is to be further urg'd, If the Time of this <hi>Kingdom</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> be not generally known, and agreed upon, it can do but little Service for the Inlightning the <hi>dark place of the Apoſtacy;</hi> and that we do not find it hath been; and if <hi>Prophecy</hi> be not in its own Conſtitution of <hi>private Interpretation,</hi> yet if it hath Eventually proved ſo, how is the <hi>Light</hi> of it ſeen?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. It is very agreeable to the Wiſdom and Glory of God, that the Fountains of Truth ſhould be running, and the Lights of it ſhining, though the Streams and Rays are not recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, nor have their kindly Effect; as the <hi>Evangeliſt John</hi> ſays, <hi>The Light ſhineth in darkneſs,</hi> though <hi>the darkneſs comprehend it not. God left not himſelf without Witneſs among the Heathen,</hi> though we know of Few who <hi>received the Teſtimony,</hi> Acts 14. 17. How many have the Goſpel-Light without its proper ſaving Effect!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. There hath been a ſtrange Collineation, or Level<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and Aiming of the Servants of God upon the Years of this Laſt Part of this <hi>Seventeenth Century,</hi> for the <hi>Glory of Chriſt's Kingdom;</hi> and beſides ſome Later, a <hi>Prophecy</hi> found in the Study of <hi>Juſtus Lipſius</hi> tranſcrib'd into the Preface of Dr. <hi>Mayer,</hi> to the Volume of his <hi>Interpretation</hi> on the <hi>Prophets Great and Small,</hi> is perpendicular on the Year Ninety Eight, in ſuch a Language as ſpeaks Effects begun, and in their Courſe as at Ninety Seven, as ſhall Appear in a ſhort Appendix to this Treatiſe.</p>
            <p>But to All that hath been ſaid, it may be added, in ſatiſfaction of the Principal Objection; that ſuppoſes <hi>Prophecy</hi> hath not been underſtood till fullfilled. It is very plain, we cannot give a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Account what Light God may have given his Servants into <hi>Prophecy</hi> in any Times. He gave <hi>Noah</hi> the Exact Time of an Hundred and Twenty Years before the <hi>Flood;</hi> to <hi>Abraham</hi> Four
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:171163:16"/> Hundred years from the Time of that <hi>Oracle</hi> to his <hi>ſeed</hi> Return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the <hi>Egyptian Nation,</hi> after God had <hi>Judg'd</hi> them; Till which time They were under that oppreſſion; According to which <hi>Moſes</hi> very Probably thought, <hi>His brethren would</hi> have <hi>underſtood, God</hi> would <hi>deliver his people</hi> by his <hi>hand;</hi> Becauſe it grew ſo near the time, and <hi>Moſes</hi> was a perſon ſo ſignalized by God in his miraculous preſervation, and his having the offer of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>called the Son of Pharoahs</hi> daughter, and yet <hi>Refuſing</hi> that Glit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Honour, as mark'd out by God for much Higher, <hi>viz.</hi> In the <hi>deliverance</hi> of his <hi>People, with whom he Choſe to ſuffer Affliction rather then to enjoy the pleaſures</hi> of <hi>ſin for</hi> a <hi>ſeaſon.</hi> Of all which I have no doubt, He had the notices from the four hundred years, He knew were Given to <hi>Abraham; The Children of Iſſachar were men, that had Knowledge,</hi> and <hi>underſtanding of Times,</hi> and <hi>Knew</hi> what <hi>Iſrael ought to Do;</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12. 32. And undoubtedly ſome <hi>Oracular</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions they had Joyn'd with <hi>Jacobs Prophecy,</hi> by which they knew, <hi>Judahs being a Royal Tribe,</hi> and that the <hi>Lyon</hi> of the <hi>Tribe</hi> was the <hi>Emblem</hi> of it, even till Chriſt, the <hi>Lyon</hi> indeed of it; and they Collected <hi>Davids</hi> Royalty ſhould then begin; <hi>Daniel underſtood by Books,</hi> not onely the <hi>Book</hi> of the <hi>Prophet Jeremy;</hi> But (as we may very Reaſonably ſuppoſe) by the <hi>Books</hi> of other Servants of God, that Kept, or Searched Records of Times, according to <hi>Jeremies Prophecy;</hi> I doubt not, <hi>Simeon Waited</hi> for <hi>the Conſolation of Iſrael</hi> according to <hi>Daniels Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty Weeks.</hi> What Light God gave to his ſervants in the Firſt times of Chriſtianity, we have not ſuch certain accounts as might be deſired: But as it is reported to us by <hi>Eccleſiaſtick Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> It was foretold of <hi>Julian,</hi> he was <hi>Nubecula cito Tranſitura,</hi> a <hi>Cloud tbat would ſoon vaniſh.</hi> But this I am ſure was according to <hi>Prophecy,</hi> that <hi>Sathan</hi> being <hi>caſt down</hi> by the change of the <hi>Pagan Empire</hi> into the <hi>Chriſtian Empire,</hi> After <hi>Conſtantine</hi> there could be in the <hi>Roman Empire no place found for him any more,</hi> of continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in its Heaven (though ſome ſhort Attempts there might be, as of <hi>Julian, Eugenius, Argobaſtes, Maximus)</hi> in his <hi>Pagan Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy;</hi> altho under the Name of Chriſt, as it were in his Right, and as the <hi>Vicar</hi> of the <hi>Fifth Monarchy</hi> of him the <hi>Manly Birth</hi> on the <hi>Throne,</hi> Satan crept in as an underminer, and in the <hi>Anti-Chriſtian</hi> Supremacy He hath a <hi>Throne as on Earth;</hi> whether therefore the Speaker had his Ground it ſelf in <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy,</hi> The thing it ſelf had; and it could not be otherwiſe, but that the <hi>Empire</hi> of an <hi>Apoſtate</hi> to <hi>Paganiſm</hi> muſt be very Short, even as of a Prince relapſing <hi>to Popery</hi> in theſe <hi>Nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:171163:17"/>
            <p>It was the buſineſs of <hi>Anti-Chriſtianiſm</hi> to ſuppreſs the <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation</hi> of <hi>Prophecy;</hi> that had ſo dreadful an Aſpect upon it ſelf, as much as it could; yet the common Fame and Bruit of <hi>Anti-Chriſts</hi> coming was ſpread far and near, when the <hi>Chriſtian Empire,</hi> which was the <hi>Let,</hi> according to <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. c. 2. was taken <hi>out of the way;</hi> the joynt being ſo Natural between the <hi>Chriſtian Ceaſing,</hi> and the <hi>Anti-Chriſtian Begïnning</hi> to ſupplant, having ſo much of the Name <hi>Chriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Voicing the <hi>Papacy</hi> to be that <hi>Antichriſt lifting up him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf</hi> above what ever was called <hi>Sebaſt</hi> or <hi>Auguſt;</hi> as he did about that Time; was heard all along from the time of <hi>Petrus Waldo,</hi> till the <hi>Reformation;</hi> and ſince the <hi>Reformation</hi> how many Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Servants of Chriſt have Labour'd with ſucceſs in the <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of Prophecy,</hi> notwithſtanding ſome particular miſtakes; with whom I humbly joyn my ſelf a <hi>Fellow Labourer,</hi> and one that hath <hi>taken part of their Labour;</hi> and now the <hi>Fields</hi> are <hi>white</hi> unto the <hi>Harveſt,</hi> when many others ſhall <hi>enter into our Labours; according to that ſaying, One ſoweth, and another Reapeth; and yet he that Reapeth, ſhall yet receive wages unto Life Eternal; ſo that they who have ſown, and they that reap, may Rejoyce together.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed, the Time is now ſo near, that whatever In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, That nearneſs may be hop'd to have upon <hi>Interpretation of Prophecy</hi> according to Truth I may humbly hope for; For tho the Time of <hi>Daniels public Interpretation</hi> upon the <hi>Seventy Years,</hi> was nearer to their End; yet the Time of his underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was undoubtedly earlyer; The Time of his <hi>Prophecy</hi> was deſigned to be cloſe upon the very end of the <hi>Seventy Years,</hi> and that ſo ſollemn <hi>Prayer;</hi> for elſe it is Evident, <hi>The Time of his praying was every Day, towards the Deſolations of</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>with his Windows open'd Three Times,</hi> with foreſight of the very time.</p>
            <p>Seeing then the very Time of <hi>Ninety Seven,</hi> I have now for ſome years pitch'd upon, as the very Time, when the <hi>Deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Sanctuary ſhall be Accompliſhed,</hi> and the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> be in <hi>Succeſſion;</hi> of which I find dayly new Confirmations, and Aſſurances, as the Time Approacheth; Therefore I hope I ſhall be Enabled, and many Servants of God with me, to <hi>ſet our ſelves</hi> dayly by <hi>Supplication,</hi> and <hi>Prayer,</hi> and <hi>ſo much the more, as we ſee the Day approaching.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 1. It may be ſaid, what is the Good, or Advantage of <hi>Knowing</hi> the <hi>Secrets of Prophecy.</hi> or the Times more eſpecially Defined by it; have we not ſuch plain Doctrines and Rules of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:171163:17"/> Scripture, that are every way ſufficient to take up our Time, and Thoughts, that are more ſure, and certain in their ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency to God, and have leſs of Scruple and Diſpute in their Senſe, and Importance?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. Whatſoever is vouchſafed to us by God, as a Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of, and Revelation from himſelf to us in his Word; not to regard, receive, and improve it, is in the Scripture Phraſe, <hi>a wearying of God,</hi> Iſa. 7. <hi>Ahaz</hi> made a fair and plauſible Pretence of Truſting God without a <hi>Sign,</hi> when God ſo Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly offered it to him; he ſaid, <hi>He would not Tempt God,</hi> and yet this his Refuſal was called a <hi>wearying of God;</hi> God under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding much better what is neceſſary for us, and to our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, than we do our ſelves; and if he hath given us a Rule of Times, it will be found to be our great Sin, and Neglect, if we do not ſearch, and enquire, every one in our places, <hi>What of the Night,</hi> and alſo how near the <hi>Morning is Comming.</hi> Eſay. 21. 11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 2. Let us ask what Good it was to <hi>Noah,</hi> that God told him, The <hi>Old World</hi> ſhould have only the Reprieve of an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and Twenty years before the <hi>Flood?</hi> What Good was it to <hi>Abraham,</hi> when God told him, It ſhould be Four Hundred years, ere his <hi>Seed ſhould be brought back?</hi> What Good was it to the <hi>Church of the Jews</hi> to be aſſured, the <hi>Babyloniſh captivity ſhould be but Seventy VVeeks;</hi> and that there ſhould be but <hi>Seven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty weeks</hi> of years from the full Reſtoring <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Meſſiah?</hi> Such as was the Good of theſe Manifeſtations to the Servants of God; ſuch is the good, that ariſes from the Knowledg of <hi>Time, Times,</hi> and <hi>Half Time,</hi> the 1260, 1290, and 1335 days of years, given as the meaſure of the <hi>Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> Times; as the Meaſure of the Preparation for the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> till the Glory of it; ſuch is the Knowledg of the 2300 <hi>Eves, Morns</hi> from the <hi>Babyloniſh Captivity</hi> ending, to the <hi>Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sanctuary in the New Jeruſalem,</hi> according to the <hi>Viſion</hi> of <hi>Ezekiels Temple:</hi> And Laſtly, ſuch is the Good of the Knowledg of the 1000 years Glory of <hi>Chriſts Kingdom</hi> manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to us; and then of the <hi>Kingdom Delivered up to God</hi> and the <hi>Father,</hi> the Laſt end, and Conſummation of All.</p>
            <p>I have thus far argued the Grand Aſſertion, that All, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very <hi>Prophecy of Scripture</hi> is not of <hi>private Interpretation,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not <hi>prophetick Numbers of Time,</hi> but that there are Standards
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:171163:18"/> of <hi>Interpretation</hi> in laid into <hi>Prophecy</hi> it ſelf; and ſuch Aſſiſtances from that <hi>publick Spirit</hi> vouchſafed to All that wait for them; that it is juſtly to be ſtiled not <hi>private</hi> but <hi>publick Interpretation;</hi> I have alſo counter-argued all the <hi>Objections</hi> I could diſcover; I come now to the Third Head.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Head</hi> 3<hi>d.</hi> The Third Head ſhall be to conſider, What <hi>Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dards,</hi> according to <hi>Scripture-Reaſon,</hi> and the <hi>Ballance of the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary,</hi> there are, by which the <hi>Interpretation of prophecy</hi> may be judg'd to be <hi>a True Interpretation,</hi> when it is offered us by any one that hath made it; or whereby the perſon that hath himſelf made it, may know it to be Juſt, and according to the Senſe of the <hi>Holy Spirit of prophecy,</hi> and his Conduct into that Senſe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Standards of Tryal</hi> for the <hi>True Interpretation of prophecy,</hi> I would lay down, are Theſe:</p>
            <p n="1">1. When the <hi>Types</hi> and <hi>Symbols of prophecy</hi> in the <hi>Old and New Teſtament,</hi> are taken, All, as under One intire View and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, and ſo <hi>Analogized,</hi> and ſhewn in their Agreement one with another, as to make up a Full and perfect Portraicture and Table, each Part appearing in its proper <hi>Symetry</hi> and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, in its own Scituation, in its Lively <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Lively Air of <hi>prophecy.</hi> This is like a <hi>philoſophick Syſtem of the Creation,</hi> ſolving All <hi>Phenomena.</hi> But if we take ſome ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle Parts only, though there may be handſome and fine plauſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and probable Deſcants upon them, as they ſtand by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and if they alone were to be anſwered for; Yet when they come to be examined by the reſt of <hi>prophecy,</hi> and it be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, how one part anſwers another, in the whole Frame of <hi>prophecy,</hi> and one ſingle part under ſuch or ſuch a Deſcant; Thoſe Deſcants will be diſcovered to be only worthy of Rejection This therefore I have endeavoured, and moſt cloſely and diligently attended to in <hi>the Scheme of prophecy</hi> I have given, <hi>viz.</hi> to make a Juſt and Full Agreement and Correſpondency between All parts of it, and a Conciliated Harmony in the whole Frame of <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. In the point of <hi>prophetick Numbers</hi> the <hi>Standard</hi> is,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That <hi>All the Prophetick Numbers</hi> are made to meet alſo in One full and intire Conſideration and Computation of them one with another, and not any of them ſingle, and by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:171163:18"/> only. And that they be ſo both diſtinguiſhed, and yet ſo joyned, and ſo concerted, that they ſtand fair one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Elſe the application of them will be precarious, incer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and contingent only.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That when they are thus both Diſtinguiſhed and Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monized; they can be applied and aſcertained by that Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to ſuch Events, as are witneſſed to, and acknowledged by the moſt known, agreed and general Records of <hi>Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Chronology;</hi> providentially prepared by God to <hi>Gibeonite,</hi> as it were, to <hi>Sacred Prophecy;</hi> to give both Teſtimony to the Truth of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> as alſo to be Helps to the <hi>Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it;</hi> if <hi>Interpreters</hi> take care to compare one with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or would be perſwaded to do ſo. Furthermore, theſe being ſo ſettled by Compare, and ſo Teſtified, enable the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter</hi> himſelf, and thoſe to whom his <hi>Interpretation</hi> is offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to Judge whether the <hi>Interpretation</hi> be True, and whether it be <hi>Just</hi> and <hi>Right:</hi> Whereas, if either there be no Concord of Supporting <hi>Hiſtory;</hi> or that if it be not as a <hi>City on an Hill, Hiſtory</hi> univerſally Known, and agreed; the <hi>Interpretation</hi> will be but Dark and Lubricous, and the ſtanding upon it not firm and ſtable.</p>
            <p n="3">3. When the <hi>Prophetical Numbers</hi> being by Fair and Juſt Commiſſures, Joyn'd to, and United with the Plain <hi>Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> firſt Part of the <hi>Scripture-Line of Time,</hi> Run on together in a ſtrait, even, progreſſive Motion, from the <hi>Creation</hi> and <hi>first Sabbatiſm,</hi> ſo as to Run upon a Laſt Iſſue and Event; Great enough to be that Laſt, and to conſtitute a <hi>Fullneſs of Times,</hi> or of <hi>All Times;</hi> the <hi>New Creation and its Sabbatiſm,</hi> the <hi>Apocata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſis,</hi> or <hi>Reſtitution of All Things</hi> to the Firſt State, and much above it; the <hi>Anacephalaioſis,</hi> or Bringing All under Chriſt, as the <hi>Head:</hi> And all This, as I ſaid, in a Strait, Even, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſive Motion, Taking in at their Juſt and Proper Seaſons All other Great and <hi>Cardinal</hi> Events, Emboſſing the <hi>Line of Time;</hi> and principally that Great and Soveraign One, the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, Dying, Riſing and Aſcenſion</hi> of our Lord Jeſus into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſtyl'd by the Apoſtle, <hi>the Fullneſs of Time;</hi> the greateſt Honour of Time, except the Forenamed <hi>Fullneſs of All Times.</hi> Theſe Two, <hi>The Fullneſs of Time;</hi> and the <hi>Fullneſs of Times,</hi> or of <hi>All Times,</hi> ſtand thus Diſtinguiſhed, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 4. and <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 10. <hi>and Fix all Time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now This Conſtant, Even Progreſſion of Time, keeps All <hi>Interpretation</hi> at a Gauge, and at a Certainty, from a Fugitive,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:171163:19"/> or Arbitrarious wandring hither and thither; and is the greateſt ſecurity for the Truth of it; both to the <hi>Interpreter</hi> himſelf, and to All that would put his <hi>Interpretation</hi> to the Teſt, that can be; For thus Nothing can be taken in, nor thruſt out at pleaſure; nor can there be Any Other Events ſhuffled in, but what are found in that very Juſt and Natural Order of Time, according to all <hi>Hiſtory.</hi> Thus <hi>Interpretation</hi> comes to the ſame Certainty as the Progreſſes of Time it ſelf; from Day to Day, Month to Month, Year to Year, and <hi>Century to Century;</hi> or as the parts of the Body in their True Situation one to another. Whereas any other way of <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation</hi> hath its Starts and Leaps, its Subterfuges and Evaſions, without Certainty or Fixedneſs.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Another Standard of <hi>Interpretation of Prophecy,</hi> is, when there are found in the <hi>Interpretation,</hi> ſome ſurprizing Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendencies in the Contrivances and, as one may humbly ſay, <hi>Artifices</hi> which the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy</hi> hath inlaid the <hi>Propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> Frame with, and engraven upon it, as upon the <hi>Stone</hi> that hath <hi>ſeven Eyes,</hi> throughout Perſpicuous, as well as Perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacious. And theſe falling in with the more Eſſential, and Subſtantial Parts of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> and the Events Anſwering in not only thoſe Subſtantials, but thoſe Extraordinaries, as it were, Peices of Art, in the Frame of Prophecy; They muſt needs give ſometimes even Raviſhing Tranſports of Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Aſſurance; That one hath the <hi>True Key of Interpretation of Prophecy,</hi> by the Becomingneſs of the Work to the Great Artiſt, when <hi>Materiam fuperat Opus;</hi> The Curiouſneſs of the Work excells the very Materials wrought upon.</p>
            <p>Even as beſides the main Pillars and Rafters of the Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the more Bulky Parts of the <hi>Animal Creatures;</hi> ſuch Exquiſite Curioſities are found herein; They, as much as is poſſible, give Scientific Proofs of the Supreme and Divine Workman: and when any one hath found them, he cannot but break out into a Kind of <hi>Ecstatical</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; or, as <hi>Galen,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">I have Found.</note> into an <hi>Hymn</hi> to the <hi>Creator,</hi> upon beholding the Admirable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of his Divine Hand, in the <hi>Animal Contextures;</hi> For both in the Works of God, and in his <hi>Prophetick Word,</hi> ſuch Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders plainly diſcovered give greateſt pleaſure, both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the Beauties of the Hand of God, and in regard of the Joy, that we have receiv'd the <hi>Key of Natural,</hi> or <hi>Prophetick Knowledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:171163:19"/>
            <p>For theſe are <hi>Great Things,</hi> we looked not for, and meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with them unexpectedly, we become more than Aſſured, even Triumphantly Aſſured; For thus it <hi>becomes him,</hi> whoſe <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding is Infinite,</hi> both in <hi>Creation, and Prophecy,</hi> to abound to us beyond All we could <hi>Ask</hi> or <hi>Think;</hi> and though our Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance might be ſolid without theſe, yet it would not be vivid, and ſo high.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A Fourth <hi>Standard of True Interpretation of Prophecy,</hi> is, When there is Found in All Parts of the <hi>Interpretation of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy,</hi> a perfect Agreement between <hi>Prophecy Interpreted,</hi> and the <hi>Grand Principles of Scripture,</hi> which the Apoſtle calls <hi>Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cying according to the Analogy of Faith:</hi> When <hi>Prophecy</hi> is ſo <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted</hi> concerning the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> that it be not Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented as <hi>a Carnal, Senſual Kingdom,</hi> but like it ſelf, <hi>Holy and Spiritual;</hi> That it Agree with the Apoſtles, and our Lord's Doctrine, concerning the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> both as to the <hi>Saints dead and ſleeping</hi> in and by <hi>Jeſus Incorruptibly Raiſed,</hi> and the <hi>Living Remaining Saints Changed,</hi> and as to the wicked <hi>Riſing to Condemnation, to Shame and Contempt;</hi> that <hi>Prophecy</hi> is not made to <hi>call the Proud happy,</hi> or to <hi>make ſad the Souls, whom God would not have made ſad;</hi> that <hi>Darkneſs is not put for Light,</hi> nor <hi>Light for Darkneſs;</hi> That thoſe <hi>Black Names in Scripture-Prophecy,</hi> as <hi>Beaſt, Falſe Prophet, Whore, Horns Giving their Power to the Beaſt,</hi> be applied to ſuch Perſons, and Things, as the <hi>Conſtant</hi> and moſt Avowed Doctrine of Scripture makes worthy to be ſo <hi>Character'd;</hi> however call'd by <hi>Great and Glorious Names</hi> in this <hi>Dark place of the Apoſtaſy.</hi> And on the other ſide, that Perſons and Things be <hi>Cloathed</hi> with the Honourable Names, <hi>Prophecy</hi> hath put upon them; as the <hi>Woman Cloathed with the Sun, Witneſſes, Martyrs of Jeſus;</hi> to whom the ſame <hi>Constant</hi> and Allowed Doctrine of Scripture will Allow them; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in this Thick and Groſs <hi>Atmospher,</hi> they are <hi>Bandeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toe'd</hi> with other Names, as <hi>Hereticks, Schiſmaticks, Factious,</hi> or <hi>Fanaticks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. The Crowning, and Topping, and moſt Aſſuring Stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard for the <hi>Interpretation of Prophecy</hi> is, when a Thread and Line is Laid from ſome Plain, and Litteral <hi>Interpretation of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy</hi> by the Holy Spirit of <hi>Prophecy it ſelf</hi> in one Place, to ſuch Litteral <hi>Interpretation in another place;</hi> till we come at laſt to that Iſſuing Point of All <hi>Prophecy, The Glory of the Kingdom of Christ:</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:171163:20"/> We have the Beginning of the <hi>Four Monarchies</hi> in <hi>Nebuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zars Image</hi> by very Litteral <hi>Interpretation,</hi> ſettled in <hi>Nebuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar</hi> himſelf; For <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaid to him, <hi>Thou art this Head of Gold,</hi> Dan. 2. The <hi>Perſian</hi> and <hi>Grecian Monarchies</hi> are in the ſame manner by Litteral <hi>Interpretation of Prophecy,</hi> aſſured, <hi>Dan.</hi> 8. In the ſame manner the <hi>Epoch of the Revelation</hi> is Aſſured by the Apoſtles being in the <hi>Spirit</hi> on the <hi>Lords Day of the Reſurrection,</hi> Rev. 1. c. 5. By the Mention of the <hi>Lamb Newly Slain.</hi> The <hi>Fourth Monarchy</hi> is Aſſured to be Current in the Time of the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> by <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> Cenſing all the <hi>World, Luke</hi> 2. By the <hi>Litteral Interpretation</hi> of the <hi>Great Whore</hi> to be the <hi>City Reigning then,</hi> or that at that preſent was Holding the <hi>Kingdom</hi> over the <hi>Kings of the Earth,</hi> which could be no other than <hi>Rome;</hi> For no other had then the <hi>Kingdom:</hi> beſides the <hi>Seven Mountains,</hi> on which ſhe Sate, is Litteral; The Seven Succeſſions of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment are given Litterally; And that under the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> is Affirm'd to be the <hi>Seventh Succeſſion,</hi> as <hi>Head,</hi> and the <hi>Eighth</hi> as <hi>King;</hi> The <hi>Sixth</hi> Succeſſion is Litterally Affirm'd to be then in Being, or now is: that the <hi>Seventh King,</hi> being the <hi>Chriſtian Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours,</hi> was no <hi>Head;</hi> It is Litterally Aſſur'd, the <hi>Eighth King,</hi> but <hi>Seventh Head,</hi> call'd <hi>The Beaſt, goes into Perdition,</hi> and the <hi>Kingdom of Christ</hi> immediately Succeeds; Now all theſe do ſo lead us in the True Line, and Courſe of Time, that we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſurer of the Courſe of the Seaſons, and Months, that run along, and fall out between Seaſon, and Seaſon; then we are of the Things, which in Event or Matter of Fact, and Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry run along all this Time, from the Reſurrection of our Lord, and Anſwer the <hi>Symbols,</hi> and <hi>Images of Prophecy;</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by then the <hi>Seals,</hi> the <hi>Trumpets,</hi> with the grand Events Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd under Them are made moſt certain to Run along the Time of the <hi>Roman Empire</hi> from the <hi>Appearance of Chriſt in the Fleſh, at the Fullneſs of Time, to his Appearance in the Fullneſs of Times, or of All Time at the Kingdom of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if any one ſhould ſay, Theſe Standards of <hi>Interpretation</hi> of <hi>Prophecy</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> are not ſufficient to ſecure <hi>Interpretation</hi> according to them, to be alſo according to the Mind, and Senſe of the <hi>Holy Spirit of Prophecy;</hi> I ſhould be Bold to ſay, he either Contradicts, what the Apoſtle hath ſaid, <hi>That Prophecy of Scripture is not of private Interpretation;</hi> or he muſt ſuppoſe the Senſe of the Apoſtle in theſe very words, <hi>All, Every Prophecy of Scripture is not of</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:171163:20"/> 
               <hi>private Interpretation,</hi> are, as, or more Dark, and more Hard to be Underſtood, than the Darkeſt <hi>Prophecy of Scripture</hi> it ſelf; and Further, That things may be made by Art. or by Chance to fall into an Exact Harmony with the <hi>Word of Prophecy;</hi> or that even a Serious, well grounded Reſearch of Scripture, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to all the Commands, and Encouragements of the Word of God, and a keeping cloſe to all the Rules of Scripture, and Reaſon in ſuch a Search, may be all to no End, or purpoſe; we are never the Nearer to the Truth and Mind of the <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> than if we had never ſearch'd at all; which how Opprobrious and how near to Blaſphemy againſt the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, It is ſo to ſay, I leave to every ſerious Conſiderer to Judg.</p>
            <p>Now as to what I have my ſelf done, I cannot without Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing a Conſiderable Part, of what I have already Written, and made Publick, ſhew; How cloſe I have kept to theſe Rules, and Standards, given by my ſelf for <hi>Interpretation of Prophecy;</hi> Nor will I preſume to ſay any thing in the groſs concerning it; I will only firſt make my Humble Petition to any Perſon, able to Weigh, and to Conſider, and to Compare one part of Things with another; that if I have been wanting in any one, he would pleaſe by Free Entercourſes to Remonſtrate it to me, and to allow Liberty of Debate upon it, that ſo a due Care may be Taken to Vindicate, Enlarge, Strengthen, or if neceſſity ſhould ſo Require, to Retract or Reform.</p>
            <p>I will therefore here ſubjoyn but ſome of the grounds I have reſted upon in the <hi>Interpretation of Prophecy</hi> according to a few Notes on theſe Standards, as the Next Head of Diſcourſe Propoſed.</p>
            <p>I Firſt, according to our General Scripture Account, <hi>Fix Hiſtorical Time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the drawing then into one View the <hi>Types</hi> and <hi>Symbols</hi> of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> from the Time the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy</hi> was pleas'd to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it into a <hi>Scheme,</hi> and had prepar'd ſo to do; I have conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd the <hi>Archetypal Viſion of Ezekiel's Temple,</hi> and <hi>City,</hi> c. 40. to the End: Repreſenting the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> in its Glory, and the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> alſo, having the <hi>Glory of God:</hi> Now when this was once given, it becomes a Standard; gives Types to the State of the Church of god from that Time among the <hi>Jews</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt, and in the Days of our <hi>Lord in the Fleſh:</hi> then of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> and <hi>Gentile Christian Church</hi> in all the States of it; either in the Dartings out of the Glory of it; or the Stops, Stays and Darknings of its Glory; becauſe, as is Evident both
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:171163:21"/> by Scripture, and Experience, that Glory hath been, and yet is under ſo long a Delay, from the Time of that <hi>Viſion</hi> given to this Day.</p>
            <p>Now this I have all along obſerv'd, from <hi>Prophetick Viſion</hi> to <hi>Prophetick Viſion,</hi> through the <hi>Prophecy of Daniel,</hi> and of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation,</hi> in thoſe Expreſs References to that, as I juſtly call it, <hi>Archetypal Viſion,</hi> from the very giving it to the End; And I Account it as a Pole-ſtar; like the <hi>Star</hi> that Led the <hi>Wiſe men to Christ;</hi> ſo this <hi>Viſion</hi> ſhapes an Unerring Courſe to the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And becauſe, one Principal Point in that <hi>Viſion</hi> of <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> was the <hi>Throne,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eading to the <hi>Throne of God, and of the Lamb in the New Jeruſalem,</hi> Ezek. 4. 3. 7. <hi>and</hi> Rev. 22. 3. And that there was to be, as I have ſaid, ſo long a Delay; Soon after the <hi>Viſion</hi> of <hi>Ezekiel</hi> given, There is a <hi>Viſion</hi> given to <hi>Daniel,</hi> c. 2 in <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzars Image,</hi> and of <hi>Four Beaſts, c.</hi> 7. deſcribing <hi>Four Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies,</hi> as <hi>Four Thrones,</hi> which ſhould ſucceſſively reach to the <hi>Kingdom</hi> and <hi>Throne of Chriſt;</hi> And then, as it is expreſly ſaid, the <hi>Thrones</hi> were <hi>caſt down;</hi> theſe Counter <hi>Thrones to the Throne of Chriſt;</hi> and the <hi>Throne</hi> of the <hi>Son of Man</hi> Eſtabliſhed alone, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. v. 9</p>
            <p>This therefore I lay before me, as another <hi>Archetypal Viſion;</hi> relating to the Powers of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and the Enemies of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And having to do with the <hi>Roman Monarchy,</hi> the laſt of the <hi>Four</hi> from the Times of the <hi>New Teſtament;</hi> I moſt particularly conſider that; and Finding, that the <hi>Evangeliſt Luke</hi> gives an Early Notice of it as an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monarchy</hi> in <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> Commanding a <hi>Cenſe</hi> of the whole World, as his own Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, <hi>Luke</hi> 2. 1. Even before the Birth of our Lord: I conclude this muſt be the <hi>Fourth of Daniels Monarchies;</hi> For though ſome would have it the <hi>Macedonian,</hi> as Divided after the Death of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander the Great;</hi> I find, That cannot be; both becauſe the <hi>God of Heaven would not have ſet up a Kingdom in the Days of thoſe Kings,</hi> as is expreſly ſaid, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. v 44. And alſo becauſe, <hi>The Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> Even yet, is not that Univerſal Dominion, it was Foretold, it ſhould be: And Laſtly, Becauſe I find ſo Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble an Harmony betwen the <hi>Prophetick</hi> Figures in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> and the plain <hi>Hiſtorical Accounts</hi> of that <hi>Monarchy;</hi> and that the Spirit of God hath even to plain Litteralneſs, or more than ſo, Interpreted it to be <hi>Rome</hi> and its Empire; I lay there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore before me this <hi>Roman Monarchy</hi> in the <hi>Pagan Empire;</hi> in the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:171163:21"/> 
               <hi>Antichriſtian Empire,</hi> viz. The <hi>Papacy;</hi> which to give publick Notice, it is a <hi>Throne,</hi> Aſſumes ſo Solemnly, and Notoriouſly <hi>Enthroniczation</hi> to it ſelf; and the <hi>European</hi> Kings given as <hi>Horns</hi> of Strength to it; as alſo the <hi>Mahometan Saracens,</hi> and <hi>Turks,</hi> coming as two <hi>Woes</hi> upon it, are adjuſted in Time.</p>
            <p>Now finding the <hi>Iconiſmes,</hi> or Images of Prophecy every way Agreeing herewith, both in the Freeſt <hi>Analogical,</hi> and even <hi>Litteral Interpretation,</hi> as I have ſhewn, all parts ſquaring one with Another; I cannot but be thus far aſſur'd, The <hi>Interpretation of the ſure word of Phropheſy</hi> muſt needs be Fair, Juſt and Right; or ſeeing no other <hi>Interpretation</hi> can be Found thus to Square, <hi>Prophecy</hi> muſt be indeed of <hi>Private Interpretation,</hi> altho the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle aſſures it is not ſo.</p>
            <p>More particularly with Relation to the <hi>Prophetical</hi> Numbers of Time, I Found the purely <hi>prophetical</hi> Time on that <hi>Baſis,</hi> or Ground of it, the Three Hundred Ninety Days of Years of <hi>Ezekiel</hi> his <hi>Bearing the Iniquity of the Houſe of Iſrael.</hi> Theſe I make Sevenfold, according to the <hi>Standard of Seven</hi> God ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten fixes in the punniſhment of Iniquity, <hi>Levit.</hi> 26. And ſo they comprehend in that Sevenfoldneſs, (which makes the 390, 2730,) the <hi>Forty Days of Years</hi> of <hi>Ezekiels Bearing the Iniquity of the Houſe of Judah,</hi> and the <hi>Twenty Three Hundred Eves, Morns of the Sanctuary Troden under Foot,</hi> until the <hi>Sanctuary Cleanſed,</hi> or <hi>Justified,</hi> according to <hi>Ezekiels Viſion,</hi> in the Glorious <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Twenty Seven Hundred Thirty Years, making Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Times Three Hundred and Ninety, is one of the Tranſcendents I find in the <hi>Scripture-Line of Time,</hi> according to my Computation of it, and the <hi>Third Standard</hi> now given.</p>
            <p>In this Grand Portion of the <hi>Line, viz.</hi> Of the <hi>Twenty Three Hundred Eves, Morns;</hi> Fall Evenly and Juſtly All the Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Time given after in <hi>Daniel,</hi> and the <hi>Revelation;</hi> or that can be ſuppoſed neceſſary to fill up any Spaces according to <hi>Hiſtory;</hi> or that are neceſſary to make up the 2300. although the Numbers are not, in Leſſer or Collatteral Lines to the 2300, Named in <hi>Prophecy,</hi> which Yet muſt be, and are Seventy Five before the <hi>Weeks,</hi> and Four Hundred Years after the <hi>Weeks;</hi> For all others are expreſly named in <hi>Scripture-Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy;</hi> But however, as I have often ſhewn, All Agree in their Juſt Order, and Agree among themſelves, and Agree with the Notes of Diſcerning them, Scripture hath given; and laſtly, Agree with <hi>Hiſtory</hi> and General <hi>Chronology.</hi> All
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:171163:22"/> which make as great Aſſurance, as can be of a True Compu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and Account; ſeeing neither Chance, nor Art can Tune Things to ſuch a Manifold Agreement; For, as They ſay, <hi>Res nolunt Decipi,</hi> Things will not be deceived, nor impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon; ſo they cannot be Forc'd, Compell'd, nor Flatter'd into an Agreement, and ſo manifold an Agreement; when the Natural, Mutual Reſpect, they have one to another, does not incline them.</p>
            <p>That particular Portion of the <hi>Line of Time,</hi> given to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the Time of the <hi>Apoſtaſy</hi> by, ſo often, and ſo variouſly given; <hi>viz Time, Times, Half a Time;</hi> Twice <hi>Forty Two Months;</hi> Twice <hi>Twelve Hundred Sixty Days;</hi> and <hi>Three Days and an half;</hi> and ſo the Laſt <hi>Thirty,</hi> and <hi>Forty Five,</hi> moſt Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Juſtly, according to the <hi>Line of Time,</hi> take hold of, and ſucceed one another in their Juſt Places, The 1260 concert with the <hi>Ten Kings Receiving Power at one hour</hi> with the <hi>Beaſt;</hi> The <hi>Beaſts Supremacy, the Mahometan Times;</hi> (So as to give all the Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that can be) Fall in One with Another; All according to the Juſteſt Configurations of <hi>Prophetical Images,</hi> and <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorical Events.</hi> And herein I obſerve Four Tranſcendencies, which moſt unexpectedly and ſurprizingly meet the Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer herein, according to the <hi>Third Standard</hi> here given; and would make the Meditative upon them cry out, <hi>I have found, I have found.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That as <hi>Scripture-Prophecy</hi> gives the Time by <hi>Moons</hi> to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and to the <hi>Beaſt;</hi> and <hi>Days of the Sun,</hi> to the <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> and the <hi>Woman;</hi> and that theſe <hi>Days</hi> of the <hi>Sun and Moons,</hi> are to Agree one with another, as <hi>Lunar</hi> and <hi>Solar</hi> Time do; I find, according to my Calculation, they do A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree according to the ſo celebrated Rule of the <hi>Golden Number;</hi> and that thereby the Succeſſion of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> or the <hi>Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Papacy,</hi> according to the Exact Laws of Succeſſion, to the <hi>Chriſtian Emperor,</hi> as <hi>Seventh Head,</hi> and <hi>Eighth King, Revel.</hi> 17. 10, 11. is fix'd at 475, or 6. as it ought, according to all <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> to be; and determin'd to its End, or <hi>Going into per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition</hi> at 1697. <hi>Lunar Time and Solar</hi> Falling in Exactly according to all <hi>Chronology</hi> with this <hi>Prophecy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. According to my Calculation, by the Time, the ſo known Character of Time, <hi>Indiction,</hi> or accounting by <hi>Fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teens</hi> of Years, was well known and ſettled after <hi>Conſtantine;</hi> the <hi>Spirit of Poophecy</hi> hath Adopted it to Enter into its Own
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:171163:22"/> Computation of Time; For the <hi>Time, Times and half Time,</hi> beginning accordingly at 437. are in the whole, and in each Diviſion, caſt into <hi>Indictions,</hi> or <hi>Fifteens of Years;</hi> viz. the <hi>Three Times,</hi> or <hi>Thrice Three Hundreds and Sixties;</hi> and the <hi>Half Time,</hi> or the <hi>One Hundred Eighty;</hi> and for their ſakes the <hi>Thirty,</hi> making 1260 1290, by Two <hi>Fifteens;</hi> and the <hi>Forty Five</hi> making 1290 to be 1335. <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. 11. 12. is evidently by Three <hi>Indictions,</hi> or <hi>Fifteens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to All this may be added the Obſervation, that the Words choſen out by the Spirit of God in the <hi>Chaldee, Hebrew,</hi> and <hi>Greek,</hi> to expreſs <hi>Time, Times and Half Time,</hi> ſo Sworn by Chriſt, as to be Determinate Time, may be Emphatically Tranſlated <hi>Indiction,</hi> or <hi>Indicted Time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now what can this mean? but that, Over-Ruling Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſo Diſpoſes All, that ſuch Notations of Time ſhould be found out, and come into Uſe, as when it ſelf hath Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion for them to Aſcertain its own <hi>Calendar of Prophetick Time;</hi> and who alſo would Direct, and Guide his Servants into the Obſervation of, and moſt Aſſured Diſtinction of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetick Time</hi> by Them; according to the fit Seaſons appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by himſelf, to make them ſo known to them; ſo that it is no wonder they have not been known before; or that they are made known to ſome, and not to others, when they are made known.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is even of Tranſcendent Remark, that the <hi>Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> at that ſo Agreed <hi>Epoch</hi> of it, ſhould be at 1517. as the juſt Point of <hi>Half Time</hi> beginning; that neceſſarily caſts the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the <hi>Time and Times</hi> upon 437. according to my Fixa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it; before (I can Truely Appeal) I had made a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection upon the Wonderful Service it does to aſſure the <hi>Line of Time,</hi> and the beginning of thoſe 1260 days, at 437; but accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Natural Progreſs of the 2300 <hi>Eves, Morns,</hi> in the Aſſignation of Each to their Proper Points of Time Adorn'd with their Suitable Events; Each, I ſay, of the Collatteral Lines ſo Aſſign'd Led me to 97.</p>
            <p>Now all theſe Tranſcendencies of Evidence concerning the juſt Interpretation of Prophecy, I have from Time to Time fully opened, declar'd, and argued in their Proper Treatiſes, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to further and further Light, Euidence and Aſſurance, given in by the <hi>Father of Lights;</hi> and which are in many Hands.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That which it hath pleaſed the Lord further to open and manifeſt to his Unworthy Servant, by way of <hi>Tranſeendency,</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:171163:23"/> is; That whereas I was led to fix upon 437. as the Beginning of the Times given to the <hi>Apoſtaſy,</hi> as I ſaid by the moſt Free, and Natural Progreſs upon the Line of the 2300 <hi>Eves, Morns;</hi> Diſtributed into the Particular, Leſſer and Collatteral Lines: The very Year 437. lay only amongſt the Years of Great E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents, moſt Agreeable to all the Prophetical Characters of that Time; But it ſelf was unadorn'd, and lay bare from any No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Event, or Events to guard it; and it hath been charg'd by ſeveral, as an Objection againſt my Fixing ſo poſitively up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it. But by Further Search, and particularly help'd by that Worthy <hi>Annotator</hi> on the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Annotat. on the</hi> Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> 
               <hi>Revelation,</hi> I find that Year very Notably Remark'd, with Events ſuitable to ſuch an <hi>Epoch,</hi> or Year, Beginning the 1260 Years, as it does. And that this may be Fully underſtood, I will ſomewhat more at Large Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe it; Becauſe I have not in any Treatiſe upon Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Subjects, had the ſo Attent Conſideration of it, as it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires; eſpecially being charg'd as an Objection againſt it, that there are no Reaſons in Hiſtory to reſt ſo upon it.</p>
            <p>Now then firſt, I muſt premiſe, that there is not the ſame Reaſon to expect ſo particular an Illuſtration of it by any <hi>pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Event,</hi> as in ſome Caſes in the <hi>Line of Time,</hi> For the <hi>Line of Time</hi> it ſelf muſt Umpire, and Determine which ſhall be ſuch, or ſuch an <hi>Epoch,</hi> or Point of Beginning; when a Great Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or Similarity of Euents gives a Likelyhood to One Point of Time, as much as to another.</p>
            <p>Thus when the <hi>Seventy Years of the Captivity</hi> of the People of God in <hi>Babylon</hi> began, (becauſe there were ſeveral Captivations) cannot be Judg'd, but by very ſtrict Attention to the <hi>Line of Time;</hi> as I have endeavour'd to make appear in Diſcourſes proper thereunto.</p>
            <p>In like manner, where we ſhould Fix the <hi>Seventy Weeks</hi> begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, Dated from that <hi>Word given forth for Reſtoring Jeruſalem;</hi> which <hi>went forth</hi> firſt <hi>by Cyrus,</hi> then by <hi>Darius,</hi> and by <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> in Full; muſt be Judged by deep Intuition into the <hi>Line of Time;</hi> And to bring this to our purpoſe, The <hi>Epoch</hi> of <hi>Time, Times,</hi> and <hi>Half a Time,</hi> muſt be cheifly aſſured by the <hi>Line of Time,</hi> and Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences thence ariſing; becauſe if we would Judg of it either by the <hi>Barbarous Nations</hi> Invading the <hi>Roman Weſtern Empire;</hi> the Deſign of the <hi>Four first Trumpets;</hi> whoſe Impreſſion upon the Univerſal <hi>Roman</hi> Territories, was the often taking the <hi>City Rome;</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:171163:23"/> 
               <hi>Removing out of the midſt</hi> the very Name, and Thing of <hi>Weſtern Emperor;</hi> the taking away all <hi>Conſular Power</hi> from it.</p>
            <p>Now here is ſuch a Similarity of Events, no certain Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can be made; but as <hi>Samuel</hi> was deceived in the <hi>Sons of Jeſſe,</hi> concerning the <hi>Lord's Anointed,</hi> by the Fairer Appearance of ſome of them, than of <hi>David,</hi> whom God had alone Choſen; So ſhall we be miſtaken in the Fairer Appearance of ſome E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents to give the <hi>Epoch</hi> of the <hi>Time, Times, and Half a Time,</hi> than that which is indeed ſo; ſuch another Concatenated Simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity of Events was <hi>Ceremonialneſs;</hi> preparing to <hi>Superſtition; Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition to Idolatry; So Love</hi> of <hi>Pre-eminence</hi> preparing to <hi>Hierarchy, Hierarchy</hi> to <hi>Papacy;</hi> and this from the very <hi>working of the myſtery of Iniquity</hi> in the Apoſtles days, until the <hi>Beast,</hi> or that <hi>Papacy</hi> entring into its <hi>Succeſſion;</hi> when the <hi>Roman Empire</hi> ceaſing, <hi>viz.</hi> at 476. That Name of <hi>Biſhop</hi> then, and to this Day by an Eſpecial Ordination of Providence was the Sole Title of a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle Perſon over that <hi>great City Rome</hi> (tho in Spirituals) who thence Roſe to <hi>Supremacy</hi> over all Biſhops. Thence he came to his <hi>Number</hi> in having an <hi>Image</hi> made to himſelf in the Worſhip of <hi>Images,</hi> ſettled by the 2d <hi>Councel</hi> of <hi>Nice;</hi> and Aſſuming Power over <hi>Emperors,</hi> from that Time, to the <hi>Exalting himſelf above All Styled, Auguſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in ſuch Chain ſhot Events, as theſe may be Juſtly De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominated, No ſingle Event either ought or can expreſs the <hi>Epoch;</hi> For neither in Nature can a Chain of Events ſuffer it ſelf to be engroſs'd by any One, nor can one be Comprehenſive of All, tho it be a very grand, and principal one; indeed when any Epoch is wholly, and fully Comprehended in one Event, then the Time is Fixed, and ſolely Determined by it; as the Ceſſation of the <hi>Chriſtian Empire</hi> in the <hi>Weſt,</hi> as in one <hi>Indiviſible Point,</hi> fixes the very Succeſſion of the <hi>Seventh Head,</hi> and <hi>Eighth King,</hi> call'd the <hi>Beaſt;</hi> together with the <hi>Ten Kings Receiving Power,</hi> at the ſame Time with him. In the <hi>Reformation,</hi> tho the Event indeed did not conſiſt in an Indiviſible Point; yet in that it began the Retrenchment of the <hi>Papal Power,</hi> that had ſo long been Intire; It was as in an Indiviſible Point of one ſtraight, or Right Line Drawn out.</p>
            <p>But indeed in the very whole Courſe of Events, the Plumb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the <hi>Line of Time,</hi> and comparing every part of the Line with the Event, and of the Event with the Line is the moſt Stable, and Satisfactory Aſſurance that can be Given; and in ſuch a Multiplicity of Events Frees from Diſtraction, and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity:
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:171163:24"/> And this hath given me <hi>Plerophory</hi> of <hi>Aſſurance,</hi> as from the <hi>Bright Shining of the ſure Word of Prophecy</hi> in the midſt of ſo many Miſtakes, and ſo much Incertainty thereupon.</p>
            <p>But altho Any ſingle Event among ſo many, and in a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction one with another, ought not without the Peculiar Diſtinction of the <hi>Line of Time</hi> to ſeparate it ſelf from all the Reſt, and Claim to it ſelf the Right of Giving the <hi>Epoch;</hi> yet it was moſt Condecent to the Wiſdom of that Providence, that looks to the bringing to paſs All, that hath been declared by the <hi>ſure word of Prophecy;</hi> to take care, that there ſhould be a ſufficiency of Events to Type out the whole Chain, having a Concentring and Reſt upon that year as the Epoch of <hi>Time, Times</hi> and <hi>Half a Time;</hi> as I ſhall very briefly preſent to View.</p>
            <p>When then God had been pleas'd to make known by the Types of <hi>Prophecy;</hi> that ſoon after the Empire in <hi>Conſtantine</hi> became <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> the <hi>Apostaſy</hi> was preparing to Enter; in that the <hi>Hundred Forty, and Four Thouſand</hi> were Sealed; that the <hi>Worſhipers</hi> were taken, as it were, in their laſt Appearance in the <hi>Outward Court,</hi> and Retired into the <hi>Inner-Temple;</hi> and the <hi>Church Flying</hi> into the <hi>Wilderneſs;</hi> and the <hi>Trumpets</hi> in <hi>preparation to Sound.</hi> Thus All being in Readineſs, God gives <hi>Types</hi> of thoſe Four great Events, to which <hi>Time, Times, Half a Time, Three Days and an Half, Twice Forty two Months, and Twice Twelve Hundred Sixty Days</hi> as hath been often obſerved, are allowed; and which Receiv'd their <hi>Epoch</hi> here; <hi>Types</hi> I ſay; For I have not, I declare, dar'd to Rely upon them, as events Determining the <hi>Epoch,</hi> of theſe Great Times, but fair <hi>Types,</hi> and Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Each.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Firſt Event, I would obſerve, is; That, which I find moſt agreed in All <hi>Chronology;</hi> that this very year; <hi>Cyril, Biſhop of Alexandria,</hi> brought forth his <hi>Cyclus Paſchalis</hi> for ſetling the Due Time of <hi>Eaſter;</hi> Adjuſting <hi>Lunar</hi> years to <hi>Solar,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Golden Number.</hi> Now this is very Wonderful, that juſt at the Time, when the Lord, for the <hi>Interpretation of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetical</hi> Time ſhould, (to Allude to the <hi>Need</hi> Chriſt had of the <hi>Aſſe</hi> in the Goſpel,) have need of ſuch an Adjuſtment to be ſollemnly brought in, and Avowed in the profeſſion of <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity Antichriſtianized;</hi> which is the <hi>Outward Court given to the Gentiles, viz.</hi> the <hi>Antichriſtian Gentiles to Tread under Foot,</hi> it was ſo done: For then <hi>Forty two Months</hi> of the <hi>Gentiles Precalated</hi> to the <hi>Forty two Months of the Beaſt,</hi> This was very obſervable.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:171163:24"/>
            <p n="1"> 1. Becauſe hereby Providence gave notice; that this was the very year, that by <hi>Prophecy,</hi> according to the Foundations, upon which a ſetled Time of <hi>Eaſter</hi> is Found, <hi>viz.</hi> by Conforming <hi>Lunar,</hi> and <hi>Solar Time</hi> one to another; The <hi>Moons</hi> of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and the <hi>Beasts Moons</hi> are together made juſt even to the 1260 <hi>Solar Years;</hi> And which is very wonderful, juſt ſo many years, as the <hi>Beaſts Moons</hi> want to make them equal to 1260 <hi>Solar years</hi> of the <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> and the <hi>Woman</hi> according to that <hi>Golden Number;</hi> (the very Ground of any <hi>Cyclus Paſchalis;)</hi> viz. 38 years, and ſomething more; Juſt ſo many are Found between 437, (when the Paſchal Cycle was, as I ſay, firſt brought forth,) and the Ceſſation of the <hi>Chriſtian Empire;</hi> when the <hi>Beaſts</hi> Succeſſion, and ſo Time Dated from him, as the Supreme or Seventh Head, and Eighth King (for ſo it ought to be) began, <hi>viz.</hi> at 475 ending, or 476.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is very obſervable, Becauſe as hath been alſo more Fully ſpoken of elſewhere, and as is very well known; The <hi>Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy</hi> hath in regard of <hi>Shrivings,</hi> or <hi>Confeſſions, Pennances, Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Pardons;</hi> the ſo ſuperſtitious Sollemnities of its <hi>Good Friday;</hi> the Idolatry of its <hi>High Eaſter Day</hi> Maſs; ſuch deep Intereſts in <hi>Eaſter,</hi> and the <hi>Moveable Feaſts</hi> dependent upon it.</p>
            <p>But altho <hi>I</hi> cannot but think this very Remarkable, when I find 437, the very year Determin'd upon by the <hi>Line of Time;</hi> yet I could not dare to reſt upon it without that; For ſome Attempt the Predeceſſor of <hi>Cyril, Theophilus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria</hi> had made this way; and <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> Sirnam'd <hi>Exiguus,</hi> perfected upon what <hi>Cyril</hi> had done; But when the <hi>Line of Time</hi> concurs with ſuch a Note of <hi>Lunar</hi> Time, proper to <hi>Moons,</hi> Equated to <hi>Solar</hi> Time; It appears to me very great.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Event</hi> 2 The <hi>Barbarians</hi> or <hi>Goths</hi> this year made an Excurſion upon the People of the Empire, call'd the <hi>Arverni,</hi> with all manner of Calamities; This was a Type of the <hi>Hail mingled with Fire in the First Trumpet;</hi> yet ſo that this is not to be taken, but in Conjunction, as hath been already ſaid, with what went before, and followed after; For it could not be in one year, that the whole <hi>third part of Trees,</hi> and of <hi>Green Graſs;</hi> that is; the <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories</hi> of ſo great an <hi>Empire,</hi> (of which Empire <hi>Third part</hi> is made by this <hi>Prophecy</hi> as a <hi>Hieroglyphic,)</hi> ſhould be deſtroyed. But a Reſemblance of this, Any part of the <hi>Empire,</hi> and at what diſtance ſoever from <hi>Rome</hi> (the Further, the more Lively the <hi>Emblem)</hi> might be of the <hi>Hail</hi> Diſhevelling it ſelf year after year,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:171163:25"/> through the whole <hi>Empire;</hi> Yet on this neither dare I rely alone; For as great Events of this Kind, and much Greater before and after There were; yet this, however a ſmall Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure coming in its juſt Place after ſo great a Figure, as the <hi>Line of Time,</hi> Directing perpendicularly upon 437, as the <hi>Epoch</hi> of the <hi>Time, Times, Half Time,</hi> is very puiſſant Aſſurance of that very year.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Event</hi> 3. As a Reſemblance of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> Entring into the <hi>Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward-Court,</hi> this very year; <hi>Genſericus,</hi> the <hi>King of the Vandals,</hi> ſet himſelf to Extirpate for the ſake of <hi>Arrianiſm,</hi> the Faith of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, <hi>the Eternal Son of God;</hi> and Raiſed in <hi>Africk,</hi> where he had planted himſelf within the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> a Cruel Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution upon it.</p>
            <p>Now, as in the Former, I do not Lay ſtreſs upon this with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that principal Figure, Teſtimony and Evidence from the <hi>Line of Time:</hi> But that lying in the Foundation, I Reflect in theſe Obſervations upon this, as Agreeing to this Epoch of this Time.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That taking the <hi>Arrian</hi> denial of Jeſus Chriſt the <hi>Son of God,</hi> it was in two Regards a moſt fit Type to give notice by of the <hi>Antichriſtian Apoſtaſy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That tho it be not a plain Point of that <hi>Roman Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Apoſtaſy;</hi> yet in that it is a Denial of <hi>Chriſt being come in the Eleſh,</hi> which the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> ſaith is the very <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt;</hi> It is moſt Fit, as a <hi>Type</hi> to Repreſent that, which in many grand Inſtances has overthrown <hi>Chriſts coming in the Fleſh,</hi> in the Scripture ſenſe of him, as the <hi>One Mediator;</hi> a Point as Fundamental in Chriſtianity, as the one God is in Natural Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It was Fit in this Regard, that it might give notice of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> in that <hi>Antichriſtianiz'd</hi> Age, in a Point wherein they were very Zealous; that is; <hi>the Eternal Godhead of Chriſt;</hi> in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther points of <hi>Antichriſtianiſm</hi> found in Themſelves, they could not diſcern it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There could not be a fitter <hi>Type</hi> of the <hi>Witneſſes putting on Sackcloath,</hi> than the Spread of the <hi>perſecution,</hi> and ſeveral Excellent Perſons <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory</hi> makes mention of, who ſuffered even to Death in that <hi>perſecution,</hi> though I own it but a <hi>Type;</hi> And this gives alſo the Fourth <hi>Event, viz.</hi> of the <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:171163:25"/> 
               <hi>putting on Sackcloath,</hi> and the <hi>Church flying into the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Africk</hi> was a very fit place to be uſed in ſuch a Type, both as it was one of the Three Parts of the <hi>Known World;</hi> and as it was a worthy, and excellent part of the Chriſtian Church; where God had ſetled ſo great a Light in the Miniſtry of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Hippo;</hi> who had in his Epiſtle to <hi>Januarius,</hi> Remonſtrated againſt that Throng of <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> Crowding in upon Chriſtianity in that Time; and in that, a place was moſt Fit to be Choſen, that ſhould not it ſelf be the Seat of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pretenders of <hi>Rome,</hi> or <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Genſericus</hi> being King of the <hi>Vandals</hi> was a fit Type of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> coming into the <hi>Outer Court,</hi> and <hi>Holy City;</hi> as he was one of thoſe that came in upon the <hi>Chriſtian Empire,</hi> that had been made an <hi>Emblem</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt;</hi> and as thoſe Irruptions Cauſed great Mourning of all the Servants of Chriſt from a <hi>Sympathy</hi> with thoſe Calamities upon their own Country, and the Profeſſion of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As the People he brought in were to Coaleſce, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Incorporated with the People of the <hi>Roman Empire;</hi> and ſo to be the <hi>Beaſts</hi> People, and to Conſtitute the <hi>ten Kingdoms</hi> under the <hi>ten Kings,</hi> that ſhould <hi>receive Power with the Beaſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And tho all theſe are thus very Worthy to be Conſider'd; and It Appears, when once the <hi>Line of Time</hi> hath pointed upon them; They fall in with great Conformity to the ſhewing the <hi>Epoch</hi> of the <hi>Time, Times Half a Time, the Forty two Months</hi> and the 1260 days of years, to be 437.</p>
            <p>Having then an undoubted Aſſurance of 97, as the Period of the 1260 years It lies with ſome Preſſure upon my Thoughts, to make a Judgment according to the greateſt Light, I can Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain from <hi>Prophecy,</hi> upon theſe Three Years, or till 97; what we may humbly Expect, and eſpecially under the great <hi>Pheno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menon,</hi> the <hi>Blazing Star,</hi> as I may call it, of the <hi>French Power;</hi> here the Doubt Hangs between two Points, which ſhould caſt the Scale.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether the Progreſſion of Providence in Preparation to the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> may be expected to be Gradual; or whether the Motion may be expected to be ſudden; whether things may continue much at a Ballance till upon that Time, and that then the Divine Power may, as all on the Sudden,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:171163:26"/> manifeſt it ſelf; and like it ſelf work in an Inſtant, and as it were in one Day.</p>
            <p>I muſt Acknowledg, as I have alſo publickly Declared; I have been much more inclined to Hope (tho not without, as Freely, Profeſſed Fears, and Doubts for Reaſons, as openly given) that we ſhould in theſe years have ſeen much greater <hi>Works of God;</hi> becauſe I eſtimated the Pace, I thought Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence would chooſe, and the ſteps, it would take, according to what hath been generally hitherto in the World.</p>
            <p>But it Pleaſed the <hi>Wiſe,</hi> and <hi>Holy,</hi> and <hi>Gracious Governour</hi> of <hi>All things,</hi> ſo to Direct; that One peculiar Advertiſement of <hi>Prophecy</hi> ſhould even ſtart out to me; that tho I do not profeſs the ſame Confidence upon it, as upon the <hi>Scripture Line of Time,</hi> I have given; yet I am Reduced by it to another kind of <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation,</hi> till 97. than I have had; For in place of the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Progreſs of Providence, for the <hi>Pulling down</hi> the <hi>French Power,</hi> the <hi>Change of the ten Kings,</hi> and other the great Effects I expect at 97. I have now far greater Reaſon to Beleive; There ſhall at preſent be only a <hi>Divine Interpoſition</hi> for the ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing things much where they are, and that there ſhall be nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Remarkable going forward, or backward. <hi>VIZ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That none of the <hi>Eminent Kingdoms,</hi> that have <hi>Revers'd</hi> their <hi>Power from the Beaſt,</hi> ſhall ever be <hi>Re-Enthrall'd</hi> under that Power; or ſhall <hi>Re-exchange their Proteſtant,</hi> and, as we ſtile it, <hi>Reform'd State</hi> for a <hi>Papal Government;</hi> which I now find to be the great Account of theſe ſo many late <hi>Extraordinary Revolutions</hi> within the Nations of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> and yet the Dawns, Appearances, and the very, ſo much, as Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> are ſo Reſerv'd, and make ſo ſmall Offertures to the World, or ſo much as to theſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That no one of the <hi>Ten Kings</hi> ſhall ſo much Exceed his <hi>Figure,</hi> as to be more than one of <hi>Ten;</hi> However ſome one may ſtretch himſelf every way to <hi>Graſp at <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monarchy;</hi> and be ſo far ſuccſsful, as to draw great Powers to himſelf, that he may anſwer one Peculiar Note in <hi>Prophecy,</hi> preſently to be given in Memorial.</p>
            <p>And this is that moſt Acquieſcible and Satisfactory Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Myſterious Providence in Twiſting a <hi>Confederacy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Proteſtant Nations</hi> and ſo many of the Vowed <hi>Tributaries of the Antichriſtian Supremacy</hi> of the <hi>Beaſt;</hi> whoſe Intereſt Lies, as
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:171163:26"/> Deep, in the <hi>Extirpation of Proteſtancy,</hi> which they call, <hi>Hereſy,</hi> as that of <hi>France;</hi> and in Pure Bigottry to <hi>Rome</hi> much deeper; and have been, and now are, as great, tho more ſilent Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſors of the Reformation within their own Territories, and Perſecutors of it, if any appear for it: But thus Infinite Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom hath Harmonized this State of the <hi>European Nations</hi> for his own Wiſe and Holy Ends, according to <hi>Prophecy;</hi> that the <hi>French</hi> Aſpirings to Univerſal Monarchy may be Embarraſs'd.</p>
            <p>Theſe things then being Premis'd, I have very great Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to Doubt, and Fear; The <hi>Proteſtant Princes,</hi> and the <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> under them ſhall Advance little higher, till the Period it ſelf 97; which I ground upon ſingular Remarks in that <hi>Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy</hi> of the <hi>Viſion</hi> of <hi>Nebachadnezzars Image,</hi> Dan. 2.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I obſerve in that grand <hi>Calendar</hi> of Time for the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt;</hi> The Deſcent of Time is by the parts of the <hi>Image,</hi> and ſo by the <hi>Metals</hi> Aſſigned to the ſeveral, as I may call them Regions or Parts; the Firſt, or Beginning Point of Time is in the <hi>Gold</hi> of the <hi>Head,</hi> or the <hi>Babyloniſh Empire;</hi> Thence it goes down to the <hi>Breaſt,</hi> and <hi>Arms of Silver the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian Kingdom;</hi> and from thence to the <hi>Belly,</hi> and <hi>Thighs</hi> of <hi>Braſs, the Kingdom of Greece,</hi> and ſo comes down to the <hi>Legs of Iron,</hi> the Firſt part of the <hi>Roman Pagan Empire,</hi> and laſtly, To the <hi>Feet</hi> and <hi>Ten Toes, part of Iron, and part of Clay;</hi> that is, the <hi>Ten European Kingdoms,</hi> into which that <hi>Pagan Empire</hi> was Divided; when joyn'd with the <hi>Papacy,</hi> and <hi>Hierarchy,</hi> the <hi>Clay</hi> proper to each of thoſe <hi>Kingdoms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the Order, and Diſtinction of the Parts, and of the <hi>Metals</hi> of the <hi>Image</hi> is ſo Eſſential to the <hi>Viſion,</hi> and <hi>Prophecy</hi> is ſo exact; there can be no change without great Reafon, and even great ſignification Deſigned by that Change, and <hi>no chance in it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Order of the Parts, and the Metals, is given firſt <hi>Synthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically,</hi> or <hi>Conſtitutively,</hi> v. 32. 33. The <hi>Image's Head was of Fine Gold; his Breast and Arms were of Silver; His Belly and his Thighs of Braſs; his Legs of Iron; his Feet part of Iron, part of Clay;</hi> The Conjunction therefore between the <hi>Iron,</hi> and the <hi>Clay;</hi> tho they did not mix one with the other, muſt needs be very cloſe in the Conſtituting the <hi>Feet;</hi> and yet to make more clear this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction, and order; It is ſaid, when the <hi>Stone cut of the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> came to <hi>ſmite</hi> the <hi>Image,</hi> the <hi>ſtroke</hi> was upon the <hi>Feet,</hi> that were of <hi>Iron,</hi> and of <hi>Clay.</hi> Again, v. 35. when the Method is
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:171163:27"/> given, as they ſay, <hi>Analytically,</hi> or the <hi>Image</hi> in the Breaking is Reſolv'd from its Bottom to its Top, from the <hi>Foundation</hi> to the <hi>Neck.</hi> It is ſaid, Then was <hi>the Iron, the Clay, the Braſs, the Silver, and the Gold Broken to Peices together, and became like the chaff of the Summer Threſhing Floor.</hi> Before the <hi>Image</hi> was given from Head to Foot; Here from Foot to Head; But the Conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is kept moſt Inviolate, and the Order, conſidering forward Firſt, and then backward, is the very ſame.</p>
            <p>Now this Conjunction, and order are ſo Eſſentially, and Subſtantially Fix'd, They can never be unfix'd any more; This muſt be the Conjunction, this muſt be the Order, and nothing that Comes after it, can Diſannul it.</p>
            <p>And yet when it comes to the laſt <hi>Cataſtrophe</hi> in the <hi>Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the <hi>Dream;</hi> and ſo when the Event is ſuppos'd to come to its Complement, that the <hi>Stone cut out of the Mountain without Hands</hi> Falls upon All, and <hi>Grinds them to powder.</hi> Then the <hi>Iron</hi> and the <hi>Clay</hi> are ſeparated by the <hi>Braſs;</hi> that has nothing to do in the <hi>Feet,</hi> but with the <hi>Belly,</hi> and the <hi>Thighes</hi> only; For they only were of <hi>Braſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the very Order given by the Spirit of God in this laſt part of the Viſion, I Find upon ſearch no Reaſon to doubt in the leaſt; there appearing no demurr on a Different Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as it ſtands in the <hi>Chaldee Verity,</hi> or the <hi>Syriac Verſion,</hi> as may be ſeen in B. <hi>Walton's Polyglot Bible:</hi> And yet it is, as if the <hi>Feet of Iron</hi> were joyn'd immediately with the <hi>Thighs of Braſs,</hi> and the <hi>Clay</hi> removed out of their place; and, as if the ſtroke were on the <hi>Braſs,</hi> before it was on the <hi>Clay;</hi> whereas it was made again and again, and a third Time Certain, The ſtroke is on the Feet of <hi>Iron and Clay,</hi> before the <hi>Braſs</hi> ſhould feel the Force of it; Now all theſe are ſo great Points of the <hi>Viſion,</hi> that nothing can unſettle them without ſubverting the whole Frame: For then the <hi>Dream</hi> could not, as he hath ſaid, be <hi>Certain,</hi> nor the <hi>Interpretation be ſure,</hi> nor what is grounded upon it be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaken.</p>
            <p>It muſt needs therefore be; That for the Truth of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction, the Order of the Metals, and of the Parts, and the Order of the Stroke, were all given before, as they are, were and ſhall be; And that the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy</hi> preſumes, that none would think; It either on purpoſe, or Caſually, would Deſtroy its own Frame.</p>
            <p>I offer therefore to deep ſearch of others, and the Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of All, who have Regard for <hi>the ſure word of Prophecy</hi> to
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:171163:27"/> Attend to the Reaſon, He hath Aſſiſted me, the Unworthieſt of all his Servants to give: and I am Humbly perſwaded, he Foreſaw, He would ſo Aſſiſt me, to give it in ſo publick a Miniſtry to his Servants in general.</p>
            <p>And the Reaſon is this, <hi>That God might make known to the King,</hi> and in him to after Ages, <hi>what ſhould be hereafter,</hi> As <hi>Daniel</hi> aſſures us. Now the very utmoſt of that <hi>Hereafter</hi> is very near Come, Even, as Near, as <hi>Ninety Seven,</hi> as I have fully ſet out; By comparing therefore the ſtate of Things now with this <hi>Change</hi> in the <hi>Viſion,</hi> we may arrive to ſome good de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Underſtanding in the Reaſon of the Change; I ſay, comparing it with the preſent State.</p>
            <p>I look then upon the preſent ſtate of the <hi>Ten Horns,</hi> as <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy calls them,</hi> or <hi>Kings,</hi> and their <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> I conſider, which of them, of All others bears the <hi>Metal; Iron;</hi> at the greateſt Luſtre of Appearance at this Time; and by plain matter of Fact that is the <hi>French Power,</hi> and <hi>Kingdom;</hi> Then I conſider where that, which was heretofore, call'd the <hi>Braſs</hi> in the <hi>Image</hi> of the <hi>Four Kingdoms</hi> now Reſides; and the <hi>Braſs</hi> being the <hi>Grecian Kindom,</hi> as All <hi>Interpreters</hi> agree; The <hi>Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Empire</hi> is beyond all Conteſt, known to be in the Hands of the <hi>Turk,</hi> whoſe Port is known to be at <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are then two things, God makes known to us by this Change in the <hi>Viſion,</hi> concerning that laſt State of this <hi>Image,</hi> when the <hi>Stone ſhall</hi> fall upon it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Stroke ſhall be ſtruck, and the <hi>Fall</hi> of the <hi>Stone Grinding</hi> the <hi>Image</hi> to <hi>Powder,</hi> ſhall be, when the <hi>Iron</hi> in the moſt Illuſtrious Appearance of it, near the very End ſhall be joyn'd to the <hi>Braſs,</hi> and in League with it; So that tho the <hi>Iron,</hi> even the whole <hi>Iron</hi> together with the <hi>Clay</hi> ſhall be broken be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Braſs;</hi> yet the <hi>Braſs</hi> is Transferred out of its proper, both Conjunction, and Order; not indeed ſo, but as in a <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure</hi> to give a Watchword, that when the <hi>Iron</hi> in an Eminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy ſhall be ſignally Conjoyn'd with the <hi>Braſs, viz.</hi> That <hi>Turco-Grecian</hi> Power; Then the Blow ſhall be given; and the <hi>Braſs,</hi> not before the <hi>Clay,</hi> but in its own Order ſhall be <hi>Broken,</hi> viz. The <hi>Feet</hi> of <hi>Iron</hi> and <hi>Clay</hi> Firſt, and in their own Conjunction; then the <hi>Braſs,</hi> and the <hi>Silver,</hi> and <hi>Gold</hi> immediately upon it; Now therefore obſerving the <hi>Iron</hi> in ſo Illuſtrious Appearance, joyn'd with the <hi>Braſs,</hi> at a Time, we know by the <hi>Line of Time</hi> the Blow is ſo near to be given, It is a Concurrent Aſſurance, It is very near.</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:171163:28"/>
            <p n="2"> 2. The <hi>Spirit of Prophecy</hi> is pleas'd hereby to Brand the Unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turalneſs of the Conjunction of <hi>France</hi> with the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Power; a <hi>Kingdom</hi> belonging to the <hi>Feet,</hi> and <hi>Toes,</hi> mixed with the <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erarchic, Antichristian Clay,</hi> and giving Power to it; and yet Uniting with the <hi>Braſs</hi> or <hi>Mahometan</hi> Power, a <hi>Woe</hi> upon that <hi>Antichriſtian State;</hi> A thing, as Monſtrous, as if the moſt Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent <hi>Toe</hi> ſhould ſeparate it ſelf from the <hi>Feet</hi> to joyn it ſelf im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately with the <hi>Belly,</hi> and <hi>Thighs;</hi> ſo is the <hi>Papacies</hi> moſt <hi>Chriſtian King</hi> Leagued with the <hi>Mahometan</hi> Enemy of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, as in the <hi>Antichriſtian State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rem.</hi> 2. The ſecond Remark I make on that <hi>Viſion</hi> is from yet more undeniable, if poſſible, <hi>Letter of Prophecy;</hi> that the management of the laſt Stroke, when the <hi>Stone,</hi> by its own Direction of it ſelf, ſhall fall on the <hi>Image,</hi> and <hi>Smite</hi> it; It ſhall be not by Humane, but by <hi>Immediate Divine Power;</hi> that tho it will Raiſe, and Fit what Inſtruments it pleaſes; <hi>Seven Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hards, and Eight Principal Men;</hi> yet the Stone it ſelf will be Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly ſeen Illuſtrious above All; altho there ſhall be with the <hi>Lamb</hi> the <hi>Faithful,</hi> and <hi>Called,</hi> and <hi>Choſen;</hi> yet the <hi>Lamb</hi> himſelf, as by his Immediate Power, ſhall be ſeen above All: For the <hi>Stone</hi> that is <hi>Cut out of the Mountains</hi> is ſaid to be in <hi>no Hand,</hi> or <hi>which is not in Hands,</hi> (according to the Strictneſs of Tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) or in any Hand of Man; And when he comes to work, it ſhall be as on the ſudden, and at an Inſtant. For when Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Power works, <hi>Nullum Tempus Occurrit Regi,</hi> Nothing can Lett Divine Power.</p>
            <p>Altho then I moſt Sincerely, and Earneſtly Pray, that the Lord of Hoſts would Pleaſe to give Succeſs to the <hi>Arms of the Protestant Princes and States,</hi> and moſt particularly to our own; So far as may poſſibly conſiſt with his own Wiſe, and Holy Determinations; Yet I am Bold to make theſe <hi>Prognoſticks</hi> from this Light of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> I have firſt Receiv'd, and now Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd; Partly to Arm with Patience, and Submiſſion to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay of ſuch an Iſſue, as we Naturally Deſire; partly to En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage, and Aſſure, as to ſome great Points at the Preſent; and Eſpecially to Aſcertain that <hi>Grand Iſſue</hi> of the Kingdom of Chriſt in the End.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prog.</hi> 1. Seeing the Time of the <hi>Fall</hi> and <hi>Stroke</hi> of the <hi>Stone</hi> is not <hi>upon</hi> the <hi>Iron</hi> and <hi>Braſs</hi> till 97. and that it is to be upon them in Conjunction, and upon the <hi>Iron,</hi> as it ſhall in any
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:171163:28"/> Part in an Eminency be Conjoyn'd: Therefore neither the <hi>Eminency</hi> of <hi>France</hi> as the <hi>Iron,</hi> and ſo in League with the <hi>Turk,</hi> nor the <hi>Potentacy</hi> of the <hi>Turk,</hi> who is ſo to continue a <hi>Woe</hi> upon the <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> State; ſhall be brought down, till 97. Let there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no Impatience at the Diſappointment of an Expectation herein ſeize us; For thus it is Determin'd by the <hi>ſure word of Prophecy,</hi> They muſt both continue in a Conjunction till that Time, and the Stroke with it ſo fall upon Them ſo far as can be Found by <hi>Prophecy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prognoſ.</hi> 2. Notwithſtanding this; Let what can be done, <hi>France</hi> ſhall be kept within his own Bounds, to be, but one of <hi>Ten;</hi> and the <hi>Turk</hi> ſhall be but in a Low, Tottering Condition, to be Supported only upon the Aides, and Help of <hi>France;</hi> that he may not <hi>come to his End ſo ſoon,</hi> but muſt do at laſt; as is intimat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed concerning the <hi>Turkiſh King of the North,</hi> Dan. 11. <hi>ult.</hi> Now to keep <hi>France</hi> ſo within its own Figure, is a Service ſo conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable to Providence according to Prophecy; that it ſhould make Princes, and Nations Patient under the inconveniency of War to ſuch an End; And it may Anſwer for a <hi>Confederacy</hi> of <hi>Protestants</hi> with <hi>Popiſh</hi> Powers ſo far; as that it may be made uſe of by Providence to ſuch an End as Reſtraining <hi>France,</hi> Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably to Divine Determination; And it may juſtly call us to the Obſervation of Providence, in Ballancing Things ſo, as this Laſt and former Years it has done; ſo that while, as with one hand, God is pleaſed to keep the <hi>French</hi> Power at ſuch a Height; with the other he ſo Ballances, that it ſhould not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed its Figure; So we ſee it in all the Diſpoſes of Things to this Day; So in the Wonderful Preſervation of the <hi>Kings Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> when danger was ſo every way about, and Death ſo near him: Becauſe he hath raiſed Him up, as ſo peculiar an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument</hi> to that purpoſe, to give a ſtop to the Exorbitant Power of <hi>France;</hi> as alſo to be an Interpoſer againſt the Return of <hi>Papal Power</hi> on theſe <hi>Proteſtant Nations,</hi> of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. As it was ſaid to <hi>Barak; This Journey,</hi> or Expedition <hi>ſhall not be for thy Honour,</hi> becauſe God would ſell <hi>Siſera into the Hands of a Woman;</hi> Judges 4. 9 So the great Succeſs of Finiſhing the War upon <hi>France</hi> in Conjunction with the <hi>Turks,</hi> God hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd for the <hi>Stone cut out of the Mountains,</hi> who is not in any Human Hand; No Greater, nor more Victorious Atchieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments have been therefore Granted to the <hi>Confederate Armies,</hi> nor any gradual Appearances of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> becauſe the Glory
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:171163:29"/> is reſerv'd to Chriſt; ſo that all ſhall be done by him in an inſtant, on the ſudden, at the very Time Appointed by God, <hi>viz.</hi> in the year 97. ſo near Approaching, Theſe things ſhall be done; The <hi>French</hi> Grandieur, as it now ſtands in oppoſition to the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> ſhall be <hi>ground to Powder;</hi> The <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> both the <hi>Vaudois,</hi> and the <hi>French Protestants</hi> at this Time under his Power, and Tyranny, ſhall <hi>ſee the Morning Star Dawning;</hi> They ſhall be with Chriſt, when he <hi>Breaks</hi> the <hi>Nations</hi> with a <hi>Rod</hi> of <hi>Iron;</hi> They ſhall feel a <hi>Spirit of Life Entring into them, and Cauſing them to ſtand on their Feet, and they ſhall hear a Voice from Heaven,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Come up hither.</hi> The <hi>Turkiſh Woe</hi> ſhall be clear Remov'd; But then together with this, The <hi>Confederate Princes as giving their Kingdom yet to the Beaſt, or Bapacy;</hi> and even the <hi>Protestant Princes</hi> ſo Far, as they enter into the Conſtitution of <hi>a Nebuchadnezzars Image;</hi> the <hi>Papal Hierarchic Clay;</hi> where ever it is Found; with its 7000 <hi>Names,</hi> ſhall all be <hi>Ground to Powder</hi> alſo.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Supreme Sovereign Event of Events ſhall then come to paſs; <hi>The Kingdoms of this World ſhall become the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of the Lord, and of his Chriſt; He ſhall Reign in his own Name, take to himſelf his Great Power, and ſend out his Everlaſting Goſpel, as on the Wings of Angels; and Bleſſed is he, who is not offended at theſe Things, but Loves, and Waits for them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But indeed, if God ſhould pleaſe any way to bring down the <hi>French</hi> Power, or Cauſe it, but ſo much as to Lye ſtill; and to Diſſolve the League between him, and the <hi>Turkiſh Potentacy</hi> ſooner; my Hopes, and Expectations might be, that God were ſooner alſo working by ſuch Beginnings to much greater Things for the Change of the World. In the mean Time I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but Repreſent things as Prophecy Repreſents them, and I preſume no further, And that I find not to be till 97.</p>
            <p>Another <hi>Prophetical</hi> Note, The Lord hath been pleas'd much to imprint upon my Spirit, is that <hi>Habac.</hi> 2. 13, 14. where the <hi>Prophet</hi> beholds in Litteral <hi>Babylon, the Mystical Babilon;</hi> the <hi>Town Built with Blood;</hi> the Intoxicating <hi>Sorcereſs,</hi> Enchanting the Nations to the Expoſing <hi>their Nakedneſs,</hi> and <hi>Shame,</hi> through Inebriating them with the <hi>Golden Cup of Fornication,</hi> ſhe holds in <hi>her hand;</hi> and makes the <hi>Kings of the Earth Drunk</hi> with, that they may <hi>commit the Whoredoms</hi> of <hi>Idolatry</hi> with her; and in the behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this, and the Foreſight of the End, and Deſtruction of it; The Prophet is made to ſee in <hi>Spirit,</hi> by the mighty In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of that upon him; while That bore, and carried him
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:171163:29"/> alought; and moved him; and not any <hi>Created VVill,</hi> but the <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> alone: He ſpeaks the State and Poſture of Things, that ſhall Confine, and Border upon the Ruin, and Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that <hi>Babylon;</hi> and the Manifeſtation of <hi>the Glory of the Lord,</hi> Immediately Conſequent upon it; And this State he declares, ſhall be by the peculiar Ordination, and Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Lord of Hoſts;</hi> of him, who has the Government of the whole <hi>Hoſt of Heaven and Earth;</hi> ſo that nothing ſhall be able to move to the Contrary. The People ſhall <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,</hi> as in the <hi>very Fire,</hi> the pure perfect <hi>Fire,</hi> and ſhall weary <hi>themſelves for very Vanity,</hi> pure and perfect <hi>Vanity;</hi> For ſo is it ordain'd by God, that thus he may prepare for that great change of the World; The very Reaſon, why he orders it ſo, is, Becauſe the <hi>Knowledg of the Glory of the Lord ſhall cover the Earth;</hi> The <hi>Glory ſhall cover the Earth,</hi> that the knowledg of the <hi>Glory of God may ſo cover it alſo;</hi> even as the <hi>Waters the Sea;</hi> that even as in the <hi>Sea,</hi> there is nothfng to be ſeen for Water; even ſo in the Earth, There ſhall be nothing to be ſeen for <hi>the Glory of the Lord,</hi> it ſhall ſo take up the whole View, throug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all the Earth. From hence therefore, I Argue, All kinds of Diſappointment, and Fruſtrations of All the Labour, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings, Enterprizings, that are in the World; the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations from Princes, Councels, Governments; From Trade and Commerce at Home, and Abroad; From Armies, and Navies; From Generals and Commanders of them, and their whole Force; and this not only in one part of the World, but in the Nations, and People taken together, and in the Groſs; Such Labouring in the <hi>very Fire</hi> and <hi>wearying</hi> themſelves for <hi>very vanity,</hi> are no Argument againſt ſuch a Glory of God being near, and the <hi>Knowledg</hi> of ſuch a <hi>Glory covering the Earth as the Waters do the Sea.</hi> Such a Glorious Revolution, and Change of the World, being very nigh, and <hi>at the doors;</hi> ſo that they are rather an Argument for the nighneſs of it to us. For God hath given us this, as a <hi>Prognoſtick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the very ſame manner, This Divine <hi>Prophet</hi> beholding that <hi>Great Viſion of the Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> in its laſt Accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; when all his Enemies ſhall be under the <hi>Invaſion with his Troops;</hi> Intimates That even in the <hi>Labour</hi> and <hi>Service</hi> of Nature it ſelf; There ſhall be great Fruſtrations, and Diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments, that the <hi>Fig-Tree</hi> may not <hi>Bloſſom,</hi> the <hi>Labour</hi> of the <hi>Olive</hi> may <hi>fail; there may be no Fruit in the Vine; the Flock may be cut off from the Fold, and the Heard from the Stall;</hi> And yet,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:171163:30"/> ſaith he, <hi>will I Rejoyce in the Lord, and Glory in the God of our Salvation;</hi> For tho I do Acknowledg, the World is always ſo full of Diſappointments in, all theſe Kinds, that what the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſpeaks; is moſt ſuitable to all Times; <hi>All is full of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and Vanity,</hi> as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks; <hi>Vanity of Vanities, All is Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Vexation of Spirit;</hi> All is <hi>made ſubject to Vanity, and to Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption;</hi> yet as if God would wind up the whole Web of <hi>Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> before the Time of the <hi>Salvation,</hi> of the <hi>Restitution of All Things.</hi> The <hi>Prophet</hi> thus ſpeaks, and goes on, That the <hi>Lord will make his Feet like Hinds feet,</hi> and ſet them <hi>upon the high pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the Mountain of Spices;</hi> and that then the Time of <hi>Songs</hi> ſhall indeed come in, and of <hi>Singing</hi> to the <hi>Stringed Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> Like <hi>David;</hi> at the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of the <hi>True David,</hi> the <hi>Root and Off-ſpring</hi> of <hi>David</hi> together; in compariſon of which, All ſongs are but <hi>Howling,</hi> and <hi>Lamentation</hi> now.</p>
            <p>Now if we were to Judg of Things by the preſent Aſpect of Things, and of what is in Proſpect; we may have Reaſon to hope, That the Change of the World is near; and I ſhould Rejoice to be ſo happily Miſtaken; that it is indeed nearer, than, according to the <hi>Line of Time,</hi> I can conclude it; There is every where ſuch <hi>Labouring</hi> in the <hi>very Fire,</hi> and <hi>Wearying</hi> our <hi>ſelves for very Vanity</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the laſt place, to conclude the whole Argument from the ſure Word of Prophecy, I would in brief preſent the whole Table of Time.</p>
            <p>The whole ground Plot of Prophecy is the State of Things from the <hi>Firſt Creation,</hi> and <hi>Sabbatiſm</hi> under the <hi>Firſt Adam,</hi> to the <hi>New Creation</hi> and <hi>Sabbatiſm</hi> of the <hi>Second Adam;</hi> Firſt Deſign'd, but <hi>Remaining</hi> to be Accompliſhed; even from the <hi>Foundation of the World;</hi> even when God on the <hi>Seventh Day</hi> Reſted from the Works, which <hi>He had made,</hi> according to <hi>Heb.</hi> 4 5, 7. It began to Remain to be Accompliſhed.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Sabbatiſm</hi> Comprehends the Higheſt and moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent <hi>Temple State,</hi> or a State of Enjoyment of God; and alſo a <hi>Dominion, Lordſhip, Throne</hi> and <hi>Kingdom</hi> of the <hi>Second Adam,</hi> and of <hi>his Seed</hi> over the Creation of God; <hi>All things being put under the Feet of him, and of his Seed,</hi> in the <hi>Sabbatiſm</hi> which remains to the <hi>People of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God the <hi>Lord of Time, ,</hi> hath made, and given in his word an exact <hi>Line of Time,</hi> from <hi>Sabbatiſm</hi> to <hi>Sabbatiſm;</hi> of near, or to the <hi>Evening,</hi> or between the two Evenings of the <hi>Sixth</hi> and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:171163:30"/> 
               <hi>Laſt Milenary,</hi> and allotted a Juſt <hi>Cubical Thouſand years,</hi> the perfection of Time to that <hi>Sabbatiſm</hi> it ſelf, or <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Line</hi> is at this Day to be Found in Scripture, made up of <hi>Hiſtorical Time;</hi> reaching as far, as it was neceſſary to Reach, to make up ſuch a ſpace of Time; Till by Fair Commiſſures <hi>Prophetic Time</hi> came in, and joyn'd it, and made up the Reſt even 5759 years, to the great <hi>Sabbath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the two great <hi>Types of this Temple,</hi> and <hi>Kingdom</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piring, <hi>viz.</hi> The Reigns of <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> at <hi>Solomons</hi> Death, This <hi>Line of Time</hi> is given plainly and Hiſtorically; Emboſs'd only with ſome Ornamental Reſemblances of that Kingdom and Temple-State: All which I have made out ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the very Letter of Scripture, and Fortified our <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew Copy,</hi> as truly the Word of God, by great Evidence (as I hope) of Argument from Scripture, and Scripture-Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; And thoſe ſeveral <hi>Hiſtorical</hi> Lines to <hi>Solomons</hi> Death make 3029 years; Theſe I do not particularize, becauſe they do not ſo properly fall under the <hi>ſure word of Prophecy,</hi> but the <hi>ſure word</hi> of <hi>Scripture-Hiſtory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From thence, even at <hi>Solomons</hi> Death, begins <hi>Prophetical Time,</hi> however <hi>Hiſtorically Supported</hi> in many great Branches of it; yet the <hi>Miniſtration,</hi> and <hi>Repreſentation</hi> of it is All <hi>Prophetical,</hi> and <hi>Myſtical:</hi> All and Each of theſe are of great Conſiderat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion to him, whoever he be, that would underſtand Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</p>
            <p>This general Plat-form being now laid according to, and in my <hi>Line of Time,</hi> I here preſent it in brief to View together.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:171163:31"/>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <head>THE Prophetical Scripture <hi>Line of Time,</hi> As it is Given from the Death of <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> to the <hi>Temple, New Jeruſalem,</hi> and <hi>Throne</hi> of the great <hi>Solomon, Son of David, in purely</hi> Prophetical <hi>Numbers.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Days of Years.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>FRom <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Death, when the Types of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> in <hi>David his</hi> Father, and himſelf, Ceas'd, to <hi>Ezekeil</hi>'s Temple, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The firſt Time of Sollemn <hi>Bearing Iniquity,</hi> or the Puniſhment of it in the delay of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt the Antitype,</hi> giving Spring to all <hi>Prophetick Time.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>390. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 4. 5. c. 40. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:171163:31"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>In that <hi>Ezekiels Temple</hi> was but a <hi>Viſional Temple,</hi> the former 390, years are made, according to the Standard of Seven given by God, <note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Levitic.</hi> 26. 18, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </note> ſeven times <hi>three Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ninty days of years of bearing Iniquity;</hi> in the Delay of the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt,</hi> to <hi>Ezekiels Sanctuary Cleans'd</hi> or <hi>Expiated, and Juſtified in that Kingdom.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>2340</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From <hi>Ezekiel</hi>'s <hi>Viſion</hi> of the <hi>Temple</hi> after Forty Days of years Bearing the <hi>Sin of Judah;</hi> and ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any ſo much as Appearance of a <hi>Temple-ſtate</hi> to a Faint Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of that <hi>Viſion;</hi> in <hi>Cyrus</hi> his <hi>Decree</hi> for <hi>Building</hi> the <hi>Temple,</hi> the firſt 40 of the 2340.</cell>
                     <cell>0-40. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 4. 6.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the End of the 40 days of years at <hi>Cyrus</hi> his Decree to the <hi>Sanctuary Cleans'd.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>2300 <hi>eves, morns, Dan.</hi> 8. 14.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the Decree of <hi>Cyrus;</hi> the firſt <hi>going out of the word</hi> for the Reſtoring the Temple by the <hi>God of Iſrael,</hi> and <hi>Cyrus</hi> King of <hi>Perſia;</hi> to the full <hi>going out of that word</hi> by <hi>Artaxerxes Longimanus;</hi> the firſt
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:171163:32"/> 75 of the 2300 <hi>Eves, Morns</hi> of years, a Time of the Treading it under foot; this Time therefore is Detach'd from the 2300.</cell>
                     <cell>75. <hi>Made out by Scripture Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Chronolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the <hi>word fully gone Forth,</hi> to the Time of <hi>Annointing</hi> the <hi>Sanctuary</hi> by the <hi>Powring</hi> out the <hi>Spirit</hi> on the <hi>Apoſtolick</hi> Church at the Aſcenſion of Chriſt; Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented in the midſt of the Half week by the Viſion, <hi>Revel.</hi> c. 4. c. 5. And ſo the other Half Week continues the Time of the Confirming of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, a Time cut off from the 2300 of <hi>Treading</hi> the <hi>Sanctuary under Foot.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>490 <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. 24.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Of theſe 490 years, or 70 Weeks, ſeven of them were a Time of <hi>Building the Walls, and Streets of Jeruſalem,</hi> according to all <hi>Hiſtory;</hi> Aſſuring the former 75, with theſe 49 years to reach ten years within the Reign of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius Nothus,</hi> and to be 124 years; and therefore the Firſt ſeven weeks are ſo cut off from the ſeventy
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:171163:32"/> Weeks, and ſo many <hi>Perſian</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces expreſly nam'd in ſacred Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory.</cell>
                     <cell>49 <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. 25. <hi>Ezr.</hi> 6. 14. <hi>Fſther.</hi> 1. 1. <hi>Neh.</hi> 12. 22.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the end of the Firſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty nine years of the <hi>Weeks,</hi> are Sixty two <hi>Weeks</hi> diſtinctly nam'd, a Time of Vaſſalage, Tributari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Straits and Difficulties <hi>under Heathen Princes;</hi> eſpecially <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ochus Epiphanes;</hi> a great <hi>Type</hi> of <hi>treading</hi> the <hi>Sanctuary under foot</hi> by <hi>Antichriſt;</hi> until the <hi>Publick Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry</hi> of <hi>Meſſiah the Prince.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>434 <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. 25.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From <hi>Meſſiah</hi> the Prince Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing in his Miniſtry, to the end of confirming the <hi>covenant to the Jews,</hi> at the laſt <hi>week;</hi> in the midſt of which he Died; the other <hi>half week</hi> by the Apoſtles; and their Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Deſolations.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>0007 <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. 27.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Duration of the Force of <hi>Annointing</hi> the <hi>Sanctuary</hi> was to continue during the <hi>Sealing</hi> of <hi>Viſion</hi> and <hi>Prophecy; viz.</hi> That great <hi>Viſion</hi> of <hi>Ezekiels Temple;</hi> which <hi>Sealing</hi> was both of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve from Immediate coming to paſs of that <hi>Viſion;</hi> and of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:171163:33"/> it from <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation for that Time.</cell>
                     <cell>400. <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 7.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Therefore this Sealed time is Divided into two halves.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Firſt of which was of the Purer time of the <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> when the Annointing was moſt upon it; And this the Wiſdom of the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy</hi> has ſet out by <hi>Ballances</hi> in the hand of that Juſt <hi>Emperor Alexander Severus,</hi> weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the time of the Purity of the <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> according to the weights of the <hi>Sanctuary.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>202 <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. 6.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Sealing was to ſecure, till there was a Full and Perfect <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem of Chriſts Kingdom</hi> in the <hi>Chriſtian Empire.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The other half from <hi>Alexander Severus</hi> his Death, till the <hi>taking away the Daily Sacrifice;</hi> when the <hi>Annointing</hi> paſs'd off, and the <hi>Seal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> as to the Security, went off from the <hi>Outer-court;</hi> and Reſted
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:171163:33"/> on the <hi>Inner-court,</hi> and Perſons <hi>Worſhiping</hi> in it.</cell>
                     <cell>202 <hi>Rev. c.</hi> 6. to <hi>c.</hi> 8. and <hi>c.</hi> 11. 1.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the end of <hi>ſealed time,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan <hi>Indicted time,</hi> or <hi>time, times, half time,</hi> ſo ſtil'd in <hi>Chaldee, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew, Greek,</hi> ſo call'd, becauſe <hi>ſworn</hi> Time, or Time declar'd by Oath, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. 7.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. 25. <hi>c.</hi> 12. 7.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And Accordingly God Provid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Conſtantine</hi> a Character of Time to be an Agreeable Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of Time, <hi>viz.</hi> Indictions of 15 y. to Aſcertain when the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted</hi> time, times and half time ſhould have place; there are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore twenty four Indictions that make the firſt Time, or Third of 1080 Days.</cell>
                     <cell>360 Rev. 11. 3. c. 12. 16.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The two Times, or two Thirds of 1080 Days, are twice 24 15 of years, or 24 Indictions.</cell>
                     <cell>720</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The laſt half of Indicted Time or an 180 years, in twelve Indictions making up 1260 y.</cell>
                     <cell>180 <hi>At</hi> Rev. 10. <hi>Half Time</hi> begins as hath been ſhewn.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:171163:34"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The <hi>Epoch,</hi> or beginning of the Time, Times, and half Time, is to be taken from the 42 <hi>Moons</hi> of the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> as hath been ſhewn; Beyond the <hi>time, times,</hi> and <hi>half time,</hi> or the 1260 <hi>days</hi> of <hi>years</hi> are the Thirty <hi>days</hi> of <hi>years</hi> of the Voices, making 1290, by the Addition of <hi>two Fifteens</hi> or <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>30 <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. 11. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The laſt part of Time till the <hi>Fullneſs of Time,</hi> makes the 1290, 1335, by the Addition of three, Fitteens, or <hi>Indictions,</hi> or 45 <hi>Days</hi> of years; and are the time of Powring out the <hi>Vials.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>45 <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. 12. <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Now theſe two laſt parts of Time, are <hi>Indicted</hi> Time alſo; becauſe they come under the <hi>Oath of Chriſt;</hi> that in the Days of the <hi>Seventh Angel,</hi> and his beginning to Sound, the Myſtery of God ſhall be Finiſhed.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Then follows the Thouſand years, the Glorious <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Fullneſs,</hi> the <hi>Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of time,</hi> Stild, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. Thrice, <hi>The Thouſand Years.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>1000</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:171163:34"/>
            <p>I am now come to the laſt Head of this Diſcourſe I propoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; Some Brief Reflections, by way of Inference upon the whole.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Infer.</hi> 1. This ſhews the great <hi>Price</hi> God hath put into our Hands, in the Profeſſion of Chriſtianity, of giving mighty Evidence to the Truth of the Scriptures; if the <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> that hath come upon our Profeſſion, had not Robbed us of the Hearts, to make uſe of it.</p>
            <p>For God hath given us a <hi>Sure word of Prophecy,</hi> that cannot Fail, nor deceive us in any of the great Futurities, the things to Come, It hath Foretold; They ſhall certainly be <hi>Fulfill'd,</hi> each in their Seaſon; For Infinite Wiſdom, hath deſigned, and contrived them, that cannot upon any Emergent Uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, Change its Counſel; For it calls the End at the very beginning; Infinite Veracity or Truth hath Declared them, which cannot deceive, it is a ſure word; and Allmighty Power will bring them to paſs.</p>
            <p>Now Prophecy, or <hi>Declaring things to Come</hi> is by God inſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon, as the greateſt Aſſurance of the Divine Being; <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to us,</hi> ſays God, <hi>Things to Come, that we may know, you are Gods:</hi> Yea, do good, or evil; <hi>viz.</hi> When you have Foretold them; Let the Things Foretold come to paſs by your power: Now ſeeing our Scriptures are full of <hi>Prophecies,</hi> on which theſe Evidences muſt be Founded; There wants nothing but Interpretation; Adjuſting what is paſt, to its Juſt Times of Coming to paſs, according to <hi>Prophecy,</hi> and <hi>History;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by laying aſſured Grounds of <hi>Interpreting Prophecy</hi> concerning what is to come: Oh, why do we not then concerning <hi>Things to Come,</hi> which Chriſt hath Promiſed, the Spirit ſhall lead us into and ſhew us; engage our ſelves in <hi>Interpretation?</hi> Seeing the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> hath aſſur'd, <hi>No Prophecy is of Private Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi> or <hi>Reſerv'd;</hi> even as in things paſt, Relating to Chriſt, which we ſo vehernently Argue upon againſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> and with ſo great Reaſon, why not in things to come concerning his Kingdom?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Infer.</hi> 2. We have hence Authority to Joyn Interpretation of Prophecy, and the Expectation of the Return of Miracles together, that when in <hi>Daniel,</hi> c. 12. 6. It is Enquired, <hi>How long ſhall it be to the End, or to the</hi> Perfecting <hi>of</hi> Wonders? Thoſe great Numbers of Time leading to the Bleſſed Time of the 1335 Days, that ſhall make every one Bleſſed, that
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:171163:35"/> Comes to them are Given; Certainly therefore Wonders ſhall be, or Miracles Return, when the Time of <hi>Finiſhing is.</hi> And thoſe numbers muſt Lead to that Time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Infer.</hi> 3. How Earneſt, and Diligent ſhould we be to be <hi>Found of him in Peace,</hi> without Spot, and Blameleſs; not in a ſtate of War, when that Prince Comes, with his <hi>Name written on his Veſture,</hi> and <hi>on his Thigh, King of Kings, Lord of Lords;</hi> who in <hi>Righteouſneſs Judges,</hi> and <hi>makes VVar,</hi> and <hi>ſlays with the Sword,</hi> that <hi>proceeds out of his mouth:</hi> Oh, Let us therefore be <hi>Diligent,</hi> we may be <hi>found of him in Peace,</hi> and not in the Army of <hi>Arma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geddon,</hi> in that Battel <hi>with God Almighty;</hi> this is the coming to the 1335 Days, A Bleſſedneſs is pronounced upon in <hi>Daniel;</hi> A <hi>Coming</hi> with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> with the <hi>Armies of Heaven,</hi> in <hi>white Linen,</hi> on <hi>white Horſes,</hi> as his <hi>Called, Faithful,</hi> and <hi>Choſen; with him,</hi> on his ſide. How looking, and conſiderate ſhould we be upon this Concernment! That we be found truly Fix'd in the <hi>Firmament</hi> of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> that neither in Regard of the fowl <hi>Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Errors, nor the inward Impurities of Heart, and Life, we are as <hi>mandring,</hi> and <hi>Falling Stars,</hi> for whom is <hi>reſerv'd the black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Darkneſs for ever;</hi> but may ſhine, as the <hi>Stars,</hi> and as the <hi>Firmament,</hi> Fix'd in that <hi>Firmament of Chriſtianity;</hi> by the light of which Holy Men are now <hi>wiſe to win Souls,</hi> and to <hi>turn many to Righteouſneſs;</hi> from which Antichriſt by <hi>Tranſgreſſion Fell, as a Star from Heaven upon Earth, and went down to Open that bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Pit,</hi> and fill'd the World with <hi>Darkneſs</hi> and <hi>Smoke;</hi> and ſhall be caſt into his own place at that day, the <hi>Lake</hi> that Burns <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 9. 1.</note> with <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Brimſtone;</hi> But the <hi>Righteous</hi> ſhall ſhine forth as the <hi>Sun</hi> in the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of their <hi>Father,</hi> in the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> with <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>Lamb;</hi> and <hi>for Ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If theſe Things ſeem hard to be underſtood, let us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>grow in Grace,</hi> and in the <hi>Knowledg of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt. To him be Glory for Ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:171163:35"/>
            <head>An APPENDIX.</head>
            <p>This <hi>Prediction</hi> I have added by way of <hi>Appendix,</hi> concerning Greateſt Revolutions in the ſo near Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching Year, 1698.</p>
            <p>Found in the Study of that eminent, Learned Perſon, <hi>Juſtus Lipſius,</hi> who Dyed in the year 1606.</p>
            <p>Tranſcribed by Dr. <hi>Mayer,</hi> into his Preface upon all the Prophets, publiſhed 1653. and there to be ſeen by any who will inſpect it.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated, and Remark'd upon according to its Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with <hi>Scripture Prophecy, and the Line of it's Time</hi> explain'd in ſeveral Diſcourſes; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrating, the <hi>time, times and half time ſworn</hi> by Chriſt, as the ſpace of the Antichriſtian Apoſtaſy ſhall end in the year 1697. And ſo theſe ſo Grand Events appear in a ſettlement and Conſiſtency, 1698.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <head>The Original PREDICTION.</head>
                  <l>POſt Mille Expletos a Partu Virginis Annos,</l>
                  <l>Et poſt ſexcentos Rurſus ab Orbe Datos,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nonageſimus Octavus,</hi> Mirabilis Annus</l>
                  <l>Ingruet; Isſecum Gaudia Laeta Feret.</l>
                  <l>Corruet hoc Anno <hi>Turcarum</hi> Inviſa Propago;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Roma,</hi> Tuum in Libris Fabula Nomen Erit,</l>
                  <l>Omnia Tunc Ibunt Mundi ſurſum, atque Deorſum</l>
                  <l>Imperia, ut Populos Sceptra Novella Premant;</l>
                  <l>Utque ſuum Cunctas Verbum Diffundat in Oras</l>
                  <l>Chriſtus, &amp; Imperitet <hi>Nomine</hi> Ubique <hi>Suo.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>The Tranſlation.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>FRom Virgins Son a Thouſand Years when told,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And after them ſix Hundred more are Roll'd;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Then</hi> Ninety Eight, <hi>a year of VVonders Comes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And Joyes on Joyes It heaps, to Vaſteſt Sums;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Hated Stem of</hi> Turks <hi>that year ſhall Fall:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oh</hi> Rome, <hi>in Sacred Books Foretold, men All</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Shall call thy Name That Lye: Earths Empires Move</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Their upſide down;</hi> a Novel Empire prove</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The</hi> Univerſal Monarchy; <hi>Then Christ</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To th'</hi> Everlaſting Goſpel <hi>giving Riſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Shall through all Tongues, and Kindreds it diffuſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And for</hi> Imperial Style <hi>his own Name uſe.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:171163:36"/>
            <p>I can Humbly Bleſs God, I have never been ſubject to be lightly Impreſs'd upon by any Pretenſions to <hi>Prophecy;</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering only that <hi>ſure word of Prophecy, Scripture Prophecy;</hi> to which I eſteem the word, <hi>Prophecy,</hi> in proper ſpeaking, to be now only due; as the word <hi>Scripture</hi> to Sacred Writ; and the <hi>Word</hi> to the Word of God; yet it is very certain, there may be ſtill, and there is ſtill vouchſafed by God ſuch Expoſitions of the ſure Word of Prophecy, as that his Servants thereby have the <hi>Teſtimony of Jeſus,</hi> which is the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy;</hi> or ſome Eminent Servants of God, as A. B. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> had; may have particular Foreſights given them; or God may provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentially Dictate to the minds of whom he pleaſes, the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telling of particular Events, and their Times; and each of theſe may, in general ſpeaking, be call'd <hi>Prophecy,</hi> or rather (as I chooſe) Prediction; All this notwithſtanding; A Vain Credulity, a weak Superſtitiouſneſs, Fanatick Heats I have, through his Grace, Far Removed from me; and I deſire ſtill to Renunciate to them.</p>
            <p>Yet being (as I may Account) Providentially Directed to this <hi>Prediction;</hi> which I can ſollemnly Affirm had ſo little to do yet with my ſo conſtant Fixing on <hi>Ninety Seven;</hi> that I had never Taken the leaſt notice of it, before the latter part of the laſt year; Nor had I now minded it in the leaſt; but that I found it to Tread the path of <hi>Scripture Prophecy</hi> in ſo great, and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Events; and according to the <hi>Line of Time</hi> given alſo by
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:171163:36"/> that <hi>Prophecy;</hi> with which I have for ſeveral years laſt paſt, <hi>Separated my ſelf to Intermeddle,</hi> and to make, as publick, as I could, as one Principal Point of <hi>Wiſdom</hi> at this Seaſon, now the Day is ſo <hi>near Approaching;</hi> I have found upon moſt Aſſured grounds; This <hi>Prediction</hi> hath fallen upon the Juſt Time for thoſe Events, that commencing 1697 ſhall ſettledly appear, 1698.</p>
            <p>Moreover, I find, This <hi>Prediction</hi> Formed in the very Phraſe and Words, which are ſo Applicable to the ſacred Style; that conſidering both the Subſtance and the Happineſs of the very Expreſſion in ſeveral Inſtances, I cannot deny my ſelf the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, and others the Benefit (as I hope and deſire) of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſome Remarks upon ſuch an Effort of Providence; in giving to, whoever it was, a Prediction ſo agreeable to <hi>Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy;</hi> a <hi>Prediction,</hi> in undeniable Fact, many years before the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Time, ſo conſonous to what, upon ſtrongeſt Arguments from the Word of God, with the Conſent of Undeniable, Univerſal <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> I have offered to General Knowledge, and Obſervation; To Excite to the Pondering of which Subſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Proof, I have ſome Expectation; ſuch a Concurrent, ſhort <hi>Prediction</hi> (becauſe we are naturally Inclin'd to have ſome kind of Quicker Thoughts for ſuch) may not be unuſeful.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Prediction</hi> is affirm'd by Dr. <hi>Mayer,</hi> to have been found in the Study of <hi>Justus Lipſius,</hi> a Name ſo known to the World, for All Learning, and Sagacity of Enquiry into All Things; and of the <hi>Roman,</hi> (as they will have it call'd) <hi>Catholic Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I confeſs, I can give no greater Proof, It was found there, than that Dr. <hi>Mayer</hi> hath left it ſo Affirm'd; but if it was ſo; It Argues, There was ſome Obſervation Defer'd to it by him; that he gave that Paper a place in his Study, which <hi>Foretold Rome,</hi> as the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> ſhould become one of the moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious <hi>Fables</hi> in the World; and be expoſed, as one of the greateſt Cheats upon it, Altho he ſeem'd to adhere to it; I ſay, He ſeem'd (for of ſo great a Wit, I queſtion it) However bigotted he appear'd in Writing the <hi>Virgo Hallenſis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that which is enough to me, and will be, I ſuppoſe, to others in this Kind, is; That it hath undoubtedly been extant in Print above Forty years, and ſo in the Hands of many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; and that any one may ſee it at any Time, that Pleaſes.</p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:171163:37"/>
            <p>Now it muſt needs be, Dr. <hi>Mayer</hi> knew it a <hi>Predicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of ſome Age in his Time, in Aſſigning it to <hi>Lipſius</hi> his Study, who Died near Fifty years before; and how long before it came into <hi>Lipſius</hi> his Study, it cannot be ſaid: Yet indeed Forty years in this matter, is as much as an Hundred; and Dr <hi>May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> Preface in this Caſe, as much as <hi>Lipſius</hi> his Study. For the whole ſtreſs lies here; that ſuch Events were Foretold ſo long before; that there was no Train of Cauſes leading probably to that <hi>Ninety Eight,</hi> more than any other year; and that there be ſufficient Aſſurance of this by the <hi>Predictions</hi> being in well known Hands: Now both theſe are unconteſtable concerning this <hi>Prediction</hi> by being ſo long ago in Print in Dr. <hi>Mayer,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Mayer's</hi> Works in many Hands. The Sum of the matter is, This <hi>Prediction</hi> was ſo long, before 98, an undeniable matter of Fact in Print, and known to be ſo.</p>
            <p>But I muſt not conceale; There is a Prediction in <hi>Stows An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals,</hi> p: 749. According to which, This, I am Diſcourſing, moſt probably was Form'd, as appears by ſeveral Alluſions of the one to the other, ſo plain as not to be Denied. It is a <hi>Prediction</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that famous year 1588, running thus.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>Poſt Mille Expletos a partu Virginis Annos,</l>
                  <l>Et poſt Quingentos Rurſus ab orbe Datos.</l>
                  <l>Octageſimus Octavus, Mirabilis Annus</l>
                  <l>Ingruet; Is ſecum Triſtia Fata Feret:</l>
                  <l>Si non hoc Anno Totus Malus Occidet Orbis,</l>
                  <l>Si non in Nihilum, Terra, Fretumque Ruant</l>
                  <l>Cuncta Tamen Mundi ſurſum, Ibuntque Retrorſum</l>
                  <l>Imperia, &amp; Luctus undique Grandis Erit. </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>There Engliſhed thus</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>When after Chriſts Birth, there ſhall be expir'd,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of Hundreds Fifteen years, Eeighty and Eight;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Then comes the Time of Danger to be fear'd,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And all mankind with Dolors it ſhall fright;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For if the World that year ſhall not fall,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>If Sea and Land then Periſh, ne decay,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Yet States and Kingdoms then alter ſhall,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And men to eaſe themſelves ſhall have no way.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>Now this laſt Recited <hi>Prediction</hi> is ſaid to be written by <hi>Regio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>montanus,</hi> that moſt Famous <hi>Aſtronomer</hi> of his Time, in the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:171163:37"/> year 1475. the year before he died at <hi>Rome;</hi> And the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction</hi> I now Recommend, may ſeem to be a meer Imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it; and ſo to be the Diverſion of a Fanciful, Poetical, and Adventrous Pen, wantonizing upon a Former <hi>Prediction,</hi> and Running Counter to it; and that therefore there is no Regard to be had to it. But I ſhall argue the contrary, and that upon Due Compare of the one with the other, That in Dr. <hi>Mayer</hi> will be much advanced in Repute.</p>
            <p>I do grant, That it was written by one, that had laid the Prediction of <hi>Regiomontanus</hi> before him: Nay, I make no doubt, he writ it after the year 1588. when the Remarkable Events of that Famous Year had given Reputation to the <hi>Prediction</hi> upon it: Whoever therefore writ the Prediction before us, Coaſted, and Glanced along upon that of <hi>Regio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>montanus,</hi> grown into Eſteem by Things Anſwering it; and grafts a far greater Prediction upon ſo much, as would ſerve his main purpoſe, and Leaves the Reſt. And this he did to give it ſome Remarkableneſs, by appearing in ſome of the Garb of what had obtain'd a Degree of Honor by the Effect Following it: But it indeed far exceeds its Copy; and ſince I know, it is ſo Truly according to the <hi>Sure Word of Prophecy,</hi> I am aſſur'd, whoever writ it, writ it either from a Judgment enlightned by deep Enquiry into <hi>Scripture Prophecy,</hi> or by ſome Divine Impulſe, and far above the Copy.</p>
            <p>And as Reaſons of my Aſſurance herein, I make theſe Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations upon it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In the other <hi>Prediction,</hi> there is nothing, but what falls within an ordinary Human imagination, ſuppoſing the world in an Hurly-Burly, and Confuſion; but ſuch a <hi>Series</hi> of Events known only to Scripture, and its <hi>Prophecy,</hi> not to be Read in the Stars, nor in the Book of Nature, but the Book of God only, ſhews a much higher Original, than Human Imagination, taking Copy from one much lower than it ſelf; but either a mind Divinely Taught by Scripture Prophecy, or at leaſt, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videntially Impell'd, as <hi>Caiaphas's</hi> was, <hi>John</hi> 11. 51. and not <hi>ſpeaking of it ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Whereas in the other <hi>Prediction,</hi> The Events, though ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified to be great, yet are but General, and Confuſed, and no one Expreſs; In this <hi>Prophecy,</hi> all is very great, each Event is of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:171163:38"/> the greateſt, that can be Thought of within the ſtate of the whole preſent World; each is Diſtinct, Firmly declared, Like one that knew he ſpake on great ground; this Poetry and Fancy do not uſe to do.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whereas a mere Fancy, or Humor of Foretelling would have choſen ſome nearer Time than above a <hi>Century</hi> beyond that 1588, to raiſe a quicker Expectation; and thereby a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Amuſe; this <hi>Prediction,</hi> carries ſteddily to 1698, ſo far off.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A Naked Fancy, or Incertainly guided Arrogancy of Foretelling, if it had born ſo Aloft, and at a Diſtance from the Time of the Former <hi>Prediction,</hi> would have hardly miſs'd of the Crime of 1688, Anſwering 1588. For we ſee common Expectation hath of it ſelf run upon that year, and has not been greatly miſtaken, in Regard of the <hi>Revolution</hi> in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wherein <hi>All the European World</hi> hath been ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd alſo; to carry therefore the <hi>Prediction</hi> as from one 88, and not to ſtop, and quarry (as one may ſay) upon the next 88. but to fall Perpendicularly upon 98. is a higher flight, than of a Fancy.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The words choſen out, by whoever, was the <hi>Predictor,</hi> ſo ſuſceptible of, ſo ready to Fall into, and to Cope with the words, and Images of <hi>Scripture Prophecy,</hi> are a very great Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Aſſurance; He either from Great Acquaintance with <hi>Scripture Prophecy,</hi> and Aſſiſtance from it in that mediate way, or ſome more immediate Inſpirings of that <hi>Holy Spirit of Prophecy;</hi> or at leaſt from a <hi>Providential Impulſe,</hi> or Motion of Mind was Enabled to uſe words, which the <hi>Holy Spirit Teacheth, comparing Spiritual Things with Spiritual.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6r That, which above All Aſſures me, there was a Divine Extraordinary, either Explorating, and ſearching out of the <hi>Teſtimony of Jeſus</hi> in the Written word; or from ſome Emoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy</hi> in ſome Holy and Sanctified Perſon; or at leaſt from ſome <hi>Providential Impulſe</hi> of that <hi>Spirit</hi> upon the Perſon, that writ the <hi>Prediction,</hi> is, that he hath fallen upon that very time, I have by exact Calculation found to be the very Time for the Coming of theſe great Events to paſs in a ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in 98, after their beginning 97.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:171163:38"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
